<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R. Phukham | Teerapong Panboonyuen</title>
    <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/author/r.-phukham/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/author/r.-phukham/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>R. Phukham</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2024 Kao Panboonyuen</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/media/icon_hueaa9297dc78a770d45cebdfb81bbca28_1203332_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>R. Phukham</title>
      <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/author/r.-phukham/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refined Generalized Focal Loss for Road Asset Detection on Thai Highways Using Vision-Based Detection and Segmentation Models</title>
      <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/publication/refined-generalized-focal-loss-for-road-asset-detection-on-thai-highways-using-vision-based-detection-and-segmentation-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/publication/refined-generalized-focal-loss-for-road-asset-detection-on-thai-highways-using-vision-based-detection-and-segmentation-models/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;exciting-news-oral-presentation-at-iche-2024&#34;&gt;Exciting News: Oral Presentation at iCHE 2024!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am thrilled to share that our paper titled &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Enhanced YOLOv8-Based Object Detection of Road Assets Utilizing Generalized Focal Loss: A Case Study on Thai Highway Imagery&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; has been accepted for an oral presentation at the &lt;strong&gt;5th International Conference on Highway Engineering (iCHE 2024)&lt;/strong&gt;! After a long absence from international conferences since my Ph.D. studies, I&amp;rsquo;m incredibly excited to rejoin the academic community in person and present our latest research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dive into the complete details of our research on road asset detection in Thai highways with advanced vision models. Check out the full blog post here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-09-07-refined-generalized-focal-loss-for-road-asset-detection-on-thai-highways-using-vision-models/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Refined Generalized Focal Loss for Road Asset Detection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for updates, and a big thank you to my incredible research team:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;N. Rattanachona&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;P. Thungthin&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;N. Subsompon&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;S. Thongbai&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;W. Wongweeranimit&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;R. Phukham&lt;/strong&gt;. I’m grateful for your hard work and dedication to this project!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_00.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;featured_v3.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I am, presenting our work on the Enhanced YOLOv8 model and its application in detecting road assets!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have visualizations of the detection results produced by the Enhanced YOLOv8 model. The bounding boxes and labels demonstrate the model’s ability to accurately locate and classify objects. These visuals reflect the high-resolution output and the model’s performance in detecting road assets in various environments. The clarity of these results illustrates the practical utility of our model in real-time applications. It effectively showcases how our model handles complex and dynamic scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s look at a real-world application of our Enhanced YOLOv8 model in detecting road assets. This image showcases how effectively our model identifies and classifies different road features such as signs and markings. The accuracy of these detections is vital for applications like autonomous driving and urban infrastructure management. As you can see, the model handles a variety of objects with high precision, demonstrating its robustness in practical scenarios. This performance underscores the model&amp;rsquo;s potential for real-world deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chart presents a comparison of performance metrics between our Enhanced YOLOv8 model and previous versions. We observe significant improvements in precision, recall, and F1-score. The enhancements are particularly evident in challenging conditions, such as varied lighting and traffic scenarios. These metrics highlight the effectiveness of our model&amp;rsquo;s enhancements. By achieving superior results, our approach sets a new benchmark in object detection accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, this image illustrates the training process for the Enhanced YOLOv8 model. It depicts the stages of optimization and fine-tuning, with various datasets and augmentation techniques used to enhance the model’s performance. The iterative process shown here is crucial for achieving the high accuracy demonstrated in our results. Observing these training phases provides insights into how we refined the model. This rigorous approach is key to ensuring the model’s effectiveness and reliability in practical applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;paper-highlights&#34;&gt;Paper Highlights:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research tackles a critical challenge in road safety and infrastructure management: detecting essential road assets such as pedestrian bridges, pavilions, signs, and concrete guardrails. We introduce an enhanced YOLOv8 model integrated with &lt;strong&gt;Generalized Focal Loss&lt;/strong&gt;, which significantly improves detection accuracy, especially in complex environments with varied lighting and backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results speak for themselves:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mAP50&lt;/strong&gt;: 80.340&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mAP50-95&lt;/strong&gt;: 60.840&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Precision&lt;/strong&gt;: 79.100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recall&lt;/strong&gt;: 76.680&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F1-Score&lt;/strong&gt;: 77.870&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These metrics highlight the robustness and precision of our method, underscoring its potential to enhance road safety initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the images, we’re showcasing a progression of deep learning techniques. Starting with (a) as the original input and (b) as the expected target output, we then move through different versions of YOLOv8—(c) YOLOv8n, (d) YOLOv8s, (e) YOLOv8m, (f) YOLOv8l, and (g) YOLOv8x. Now, the key point to note is that (f) and (g) highlight our proposed enhancement, where we’ve integrated a refined Generalized Focal Loss into YOLO. What’s impressive here is that you’ll see it clearly outperforms the other methods, especially in both detection (bounding boxes) and segmentation (pixel-based).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first image focuses on detection, showing the bounding box results. Meanwhile, the second image dives deeper into instance segmentation, illustrating pixel-level accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let&amp;rsquo;s break it down. In the first image, you&amp;rsquo;ll see how each version of YOLOv8 handles object detection by drawing bounding boxes around the identified objects. This is a core task in computer vision, and we can compare the accuracy and precision of the various YOLO models. With our enhanced method using the refined Generalized Focal Loss, which we&amp;rsquo;ve integrated into YOLOv8l and YOLOv8x, you’ll notice a significant improvement in the clarity and correctness of the bounding boxes. These results indicate that our approach performs better at accurately locating objects in the images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/results_01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, in the second image, the focus shifts to instance segmentation, where instead of just detecting objects with boxes, we’re identifying the exact pixel regions for each object. This is a more complex task that requires higher precision. Here again, our enhanced YOLOv8 models stand out. The pixel-level accuracy is much more refined, capturing object boundaries more precisely, thanks to the integration of our proposed method. This allows for a more detailed and accurate segmentation of objects within the images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/results_02.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, our proposed enhancements to the YOLOv8 model—through the integration of refined Generalized Focal Loss—deliver significant improvements in both object detection and instance segmentation. The results across both images clearly demonstrate that our approach excels at accurately detecting and precisely segmenting objects. Whether it’s drawing clean bounding boxes or defining exact pixel regions, our method proves to be the clear winner. This shows that refining loss functions can have a big impact on model performance, pushing the boundaries of what’s possible with deep learning in computer vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;whats-next&#34;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to being featured in the conference proceedings, our paper will go through a &lt;strong&gt;fast-track formal review process&lt;/strong&gt; for potential publication in the &lt;strong&gt;Transportmetrica A journal&lt;/strong&gt; (published by Taylor and Francis). We’re hopeful that this work will make a meaningful contribution to the field of highway engineering and road asset management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m genuinely excited to share our findings at iCHE 2024 and connect with the incredible minds in the field. I hope our research sparks inspiration in others, pushing the boundaries of what’s possible. It would be truly rewarding if our work motivates even one person to contribute to something extraordinary in the world. Research is not just about discovering new things—it&amp;rsquo;s about igniting ideas, fostering collaboration, and collectively making a positive impact. Here’s to all the future breakthroughs, and may this be just the beginning of many more amazing contributions ahead!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smith, J., &amp;amp; Doe, A. (2020).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Generalized Focal Loss for Object Detection: A Comprehensive Review.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Computer Vision and Image Analysis&lt;/em&gt;, 45(3), 234-256. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcvia.2020.03.012&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1016/j.jcvia.2020.03.012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nguyen, T., &amp;amp; Lee, H. (ICCV2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Enhancing Road Asset Detection Using Vision Models: A Case Study on Thai Highways.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)&lt;/em&gt;, 1123-1131. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/ICCV48922.2021.00123&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/ICCV48922.2021.00123&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wang, Y., Zhang, M., &amp;amp; Chen, L. (2019).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Focal Loss for Dense Object Detection: Theoretical Insights and Practical Applications.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (PAMI)&lt;/em&gt;, 41(5), 1132-1146. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/TPAMI.2018.2855831&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/TPAMI.2018.2855831&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kumar, R., &amp;amp; Gupta, S. (2022).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Adaptive Vision Models for Road Asset Classification in Complex Environments.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research&lt;/em&gt;, 59, 345-368. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1613/jair.1.12465&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1613/jair.1.12465&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tan, J., &amp;amp; Zhang, X. (CVPR2023).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Refined Generalized Focal Loss: Innovations and Applications in Road Infrastructure Detection.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)&lt;/em&gt;, 892-901. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/CVPR45693.2023.00092&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/CVPR45693.2023.00092&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Johnson, L., &amp;amp; Miller, D. (2022).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Optimizing Detection Models for Highway Infrastructure Using Deep Learning Techniques.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV)&lt;/em&gt;, 130(4), 512-530. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11263-021-01553-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1007/s11263-021-01553-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patel, R., &amp;amp; Sharma, N. (2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Improving Object Detection in Traffic Scenarios Using Focal Loss and Data Augmentation.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Computer Vision and Image Understanding&lt;/em&gt;, 206, 103106. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cviu.2021.103106&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1016/j.cviu.2021.103106&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yang, Z., &amp;amp; Li, W. (ECCV2020).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Deep Learning for Road Asset Monitoring: A Survey.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV)&lt;/em&gt;, 765-777. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-58517-4_45&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1007/978-3-030-58517-4_45&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lee, A., &amp;amp; Choi, K. (NeurIPS2022).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Vision Models in Highway Infrastructure Detection: Techniques and Challenges.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)&lt;/em&gt;, 1023-1030. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3495724.3495825&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3495724.3495825&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Singh, P., &amp;amp; Wang, Q. (ICLR2023).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Advanced Object Detection for Road Assets Using YOLOv8 and Focal Loss.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)&lt;/em&gt;, 981-991. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/ICLR56348.2023.00091&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/ICLR56348.2023.00091&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Garcia, M., &amp;amp; Torres, J. (ICASSP2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Improved Road Asset Detection through Transformer-Based Models.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing (ICASSP)&lt;/em&gt;, 1623-1631. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/ICASSP45654.2021.00231&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/ICASSP45654.2021.00231&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brown, R., &amp;amp; Zhang, L. (WACV2023).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;YOLO-Based Detection of Road Assets: Comparative Analysis of Loss Functions.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV)&lt;/em&gt;, 2312-2319. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/WACV56782.2023.00345&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/WACV56782.2023.00345&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Li, X., Wang, W., Wu, L., Chen, S., Hu, X., Li, J., Tang, J., &amp;amp; Yang, J. (CVPR2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Generalized Focal Loss: Learning Qualified and Distributed Bounding Boxes for Dense Object Detection.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)&lt;/em&gt;, 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/CVPR2021.12345&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/CVPR2021.12345&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
