<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fitness | Teerapong Panboonyuen</title>
    <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/tag/fitness/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/tag/fitness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Fitness</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2026 Kao Panboonyuen</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/media/icon_hueaa9297dc78a770d45cebdfb81bbca28_1203332_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Fitness</title>
      <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/tag/fitness/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>42.195K at Bangkok Marathon 2022 — My First Full Marathon and Crossing the Finish Line</title>
      <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2022-11-22-bangkok-marathon-2022conquering-the-full-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2022-11-22-bangkok-marathon-2022conquering-the-full-marathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;42195k--the-bangkok-marathon-2022-conquering-the-full-marathon&#34;&gt;42.195K – The Bangkok Marathon 2022: Conquering the Full Marathon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did it. I finally ran a Full Marathon—42.195 kilometers through the streets of Bangkok. It’s still sinking in, but the feeling is electric. This wasn’t just another run; it was a milestone, a test of determination, and an experience I’ll never forget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-decision-to-go-the-distance&#34;&gt;The Decision to Go the Distance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of running a full marathon had been on my mind for a while. It’s one of those challenges that, once you’ve thought about it, you can’t shake. I’d done plenty of 5Ks and 10Ks, even completed a half marathon once, but the full 42.195 KM? That was uncharted territory. So, when I finally decided to register for the Bangkok Marathon, it felt like I was committing to something much bigger than just a race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the moment I hit that “register” button, I knew there was no turning back. The excitement was real. Every time I thought about the race, I’d get a little rush of adrenaline, knowing that I was about to push my limits like never before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;training-the-journey-begins&#34;&gt;Training: The Journey Begins&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s be honest—my training for this marathon wasn’t exactly textbook. I hadn’t trained for the full distance before. My longest run leading up to race day was a half marathon, and that was just once. Most of my runs were 5K or 10K, and while those were good for keeping in shape, they didn’t fully prepare me for the grueling distance of a full marathon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I was determined. Every time I laced up my running shoes, I reminded myself that this wasn’t just another race. This was the race. My strategy was simple: keep my pace steady, listen to my body, and most importantly, finish strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;race-day-the-big-moment&#34;&gt;Race Day: The Big Moment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Race day arrived with a mix of excitement and nerves. As I stood at the starting line, surrounded by thousands of other runners, I felt the weight of what I was about to do. But more than anything, I felt ready. This was the moment I’d been waiting for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started strong, hitting my Sub1 10K goal in 55 minutes. I felt good, my pace was on point, and I was in the zone. But as the kilometers ticked by, the reality of the distance started to set in. From the 10K mark to 21.1K, I slowed down to a steady pace of around 5. I knew I needed to conserve energy for the long haul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I hit the 22K mark, things started to change. My legs were getting heavier, and my pace slowed to the point where I was more walking than running. A senior runner even teased me, saying I’d planned to run the first half and walk the second, which, in hindsight, wasn’t too far from the truth. But I kept going, focused on one goal: crossing that finish line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The infamous ‘Devil Km.35’—a point in the race where many runners hit the wall—came and went. Honestly, I was so caught up in the moment that I didn’t even realize I’d passed it. By then, I was walking and chatting with fellow runners, soaking in the atmosphere of this incredible event. The camaraderie, the support, the shared struggle—it all made the experience that much more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-final-stretch-a-run-to-remember&#34;&gt;The Final Stretch: A Run to Remember&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last 10KM were something special. As I crossed the Rama VIII Bridge just as the sun was rising, I felt an overwhelming sense of accomplishment. The view was breathtaking, and the realization that I was nearing the finish line gave me a final burst of energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, there it was—the Grand Palace, gleaming in the early morning light, marking the end of this incredible journey. Crossing that finish line was one of the most satisfying moments of my life. I’d done it. I’d run my first Full Marathon, all 42.195 kilometers of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_BKKMARATHON2022_01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Finisher medal with my bib from the Bangkok Marathon 2022&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 1: Celebrating my achievement as a Full Marathon Finisher in Bangkok 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participating in the Bangkok Marathon and completing the full marathon distance was an extraordinary achievement that filled me with immense joy and accomplishment. The race challenged me physically, mentally, and emotionally, but it also showcased the resilience, determination, and unwavering spirit within us all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crossing the finish line was a defining moment that reminded me of the incredible feats we can achieve when we set our minds to it. The memories of this triumphant journey will forever inspire and motivate me to embrace new challenges and strive for greatness in all aspects of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: To the 42.195 KM that changed everything—I’m proud of what I achieved, and I’m already excited for round two. See you at the next finish line!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_BKKMARATHON2022_02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Garmin statistics showing my marathon performance&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 2: My Garmin statistics tracking the marathon performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_BKKMARATHON2022_03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Running among the marathon participants in Bangkok Marathon 2022&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 3: Running among talented marathoners at the Bangkok Marathon 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_BKKMARATHON2022_04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Finisher medal from the Bangkok Marathon 2022&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 4: My Full Marathon Finisher medal from Bangkok Marathon 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_BKKMARATHON2022_05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The marathon route as tracked by my Garmin Fenix Watch&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 5: The marathon route I ran, as tracked by my Garmin Fenix Watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_BKKMARATHON2022_06.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;My final official result on the Bangkok Marathon 2022 scoreboard&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 6: My final position on the official Bangkok Marathon 2022 scoreboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;42.195K – The Bangkok Marathon 2022: My Journey to the Finish Line&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment I crossed the finish line at the Bangkok Marathon 2022, a rush of emotions hit me all at once. It was a mixture of exhaustion, disbelief, and joy, but most of all, pride. I had just run 42.195 kilometers, completing my very first full marathon. To many, it may just be a race, but to me, it was a testament to what sheer willpower can achieve. It was fun, exhilarating, and painful all at once. Every stride brought me closer to the finish, but it also pushed me beyond my limits. My legs screamed for mercy, my heart raced faster than I could catch my breath, but I didn’t stop. There was no turning back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The training leading up to the marathon had been a rollercoaster. I remember the doubts I had when I first registered. Could I really do it? I had run a few 5Ks and 10Ks, and I even finished a half marathon, but this was something else entirely. A full 42.195K? That felt impossible at first. Yet, the more I trained, the more I realized that it wasn’t about being the fastest—it was about the journey, the perseverance, and the mental toughness to keep going even when everything hurts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Completing the Bangkok Marathon 2022 was more than just a physical achievement. It was a personal triumph. It showed me that I am capable of so much more than I give myself credit for. It reminded me that perseverance and determination are the true markers of success. And it gave me a deep sense of gratitude for every person who cheered me on, every runner I met along the way, and every moment that brought me closer to that finish line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the journey doesn’t end here. I’m not stopping at one marathon. I will keep running, keep pushing myself, and keep striving for greatness. I’ve tasted the sweet victory of crossing the finish line, and I’m already planning my next challenge. This marathon may be over, but my journey has just begun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panboonyuen, Teerapong. (Nov 2022). &lt;em&gt;42.195K at Bangkok Marathon 2022 — My First Full Marathon and Crossing the Finish Line&lt;/em&gt;. Blog post on Kao Panboonyuen. &lt;a href=&#34;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2022-11-22-bangkok-marathon-2022conquering-the-full-marathon/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2022-11-22-bangkok-marathon-2022conquering-the-full-marathon/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For a BibTeX citation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;@article{panboonyuen2022bangkokmarathon,
  title   = &amp;quot;42.195K at Bangkok Marathon 2022 — My First Full Marathon and Crossing the Finish Line&amp;quot;,
  author  = &amp;quot;Panboonyuen, Teerapong&amp;quot;,
  journal = &amp;quot;kaopanboonyuen.github.io/&amp;quot;,
  year    = &amp;quot;2022&amp;quot;,
  month   = &amp;quot;Nov&amp;quot;,
  url     = &amp;quot;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2022-11-22-bangkok-marathon-2022conquering-the-full-marathon/&amp;quot;}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Did you find this page helpful? Consider sharing it 🙌
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
