<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>computer-vision | Teerapong Panboonyuen</title>
    <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/category/computer-vision/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/category/computer-vision/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>computer-vision</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2024 Kao Panboonyuen</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/media/icon_hueaa9297dc78a770d45cebdfb81bbca28_1203332_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>computer-vision</title>
      <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/category/computer-vision/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>REG: Refined Generalized Focal Loss for Road Asset Detection on Thai Highways Using Vision-Based Detection and Segmentation Models</title>
      <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-09-07-refined-generalized-focal-loss-for-road-asset-detection-on-thai-highways-using-vision-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-09-07-refined-generalized-focal-loss-for-road-asset-detection-on-thai-highways-using-vision-models/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    You can view the presentation slides for the talk 🛺 &lt;a href=&#34;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/files/slides/20240906_Panboonyuen_AI_ThaiHighway.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none  &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#meet-reg-the-game-changer-in-highway-asset-detection&#34;&gt;Meet REG: The Game-Changer in Highway Asset Detection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#motivation-and-relevance&#34;&gt;Motivation and Relevance&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#generalized-focal-loss-for-multi-class-detection&#34;&gt;Generalized Focal Loss for Multi-Class Detection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#refined-generalized-focal-loss-for-segmentation&#34;&gt;Refined Generalized Focal Loss for Segmentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#refinement-term-for-spatial-contextual-learning&#34;&gt;Refinement Term for Spatial-Contextual Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#joint-optimization-for-detection-and-segmentation&#34;&gt;Joint Optimization for Detection and Segmentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#incorporating-prediction-uncertainty&#34;&gt;Incorporating Prediction Uncertainty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#mathematical-foundations-for-optimization-in-reg&#34;&gt;Mathematical Foundations for Optimization in REG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#performance-analysis-for-detection-and-segmentation&#34;&gt;Performance Analysis for Detection and Segmentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#recap-a-journey-through-road-asset-detection-and-segmentation-on-thai-highways&#34;&gt;Recap: A Journey Through Road Asset Detection and Segmentation on Thai Highways&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#understanding-the-scene&#34;&gt;Understanding the Scene&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-challenge-detection-and-segmentation&#34;&gt;The Challenge: Detection and Segmentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#the-process-in-action&#34;&gt;The Process in Action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#real-world-impact&#34;&gt;Real-World Impact&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#paper-highlights&#34;&gt;Paper Highlights:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#comprehensive-analysis-of-generalized-focal-loss-and-last-layer-architectures&#34;&gt;Comprehensive Analysis of Generalized Focal Loss and Last Layer Architectures&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#generalized-focal-loss-for-vision-tasks&#34;&gt;Generalized Focal Loss for Vision Tasks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#explaining-the-two-samples-detection-and-segmentation&#34;&gt;Explaining the Two Samples: Detection and Segmentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#final-insights-pioneering-precision-with-reg-in-highway-asset-detection&#34;&gt;Final Insights: Pioneering Precision with REG in Highway Asset Detection&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1-introduction-to-generalized-focal-loss&#34;&gt;1. &lt;strong&gt;Introduction to Generalized Focal Loss&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#2-formula-for-difference-between-detection-and-segmentation-models&#34;&gt;2. &lt;strong&gt;Formula for Difference Between Detection and Segmentation Models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#3-optimization-in-object-detection-and-segmentation&#34;&gt;3. &lt;strong&gt;Optimization in Object Detection and Segmentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#4-mathematical-formulas-to-know&#34;&gt;4. &lt;strong&gt;Mathematical Formulas to Know&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#whats-next&#34;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#citation&#34;&gt;Citation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are pleased to announce that our paper, titled Enhanced REG-Based Object Detection of Road Assets Utilizing Generalized Focal Loss: A Case Study on Thai Highway Imagery, has been accepted for oral presentation at the 5th International Conference on Highway Engineering (iCHE 2024). This opportunity marks a significant moment in our academic journey, especially after a hiatus from international conferences since completing my Ph.D. I am eager to re-engage with the academic community and share our recent advancements in person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;meet-reg-the-game-changer-in-highway-asset-detection&#34;&gt;Meet REG: The Game-Changer in Highway Asset Detection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi guys, fellow tech enthusiasts! I&amp;rsquo;m thrilled to unveil a cutting-edge innovation from my latest research—Refined Generalized Focal Loss (REG). This revolutionary approach is transforming road asset detection on Thai highways, and it’s as exciting as it sounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what’s the big deal with REG? Imagine a detection system that not only sees but truly understands the intricate details of highway scenes. REG pushes the boundaries of current vision-based detection models by tackling the most challenging issues: imbalanced datasets, tiny objects, and complex highway backdrops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Our paper on “Refined Generalized Focal Loss for Road Asset Detection on Thai Highways” has been accepted for oral presentation at iCHE 2024!&lt;br&gt;.&lt;br&gt;Excited to share how we’re tackling road asset detection.&lt;br&gt;.&lt;br&gt;📖👀 Check out the details here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/KTSGHITU7F&#34;&gt;https://t.co/KTSGHITU7F&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/iCHE2024?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#iCHE2024&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/AI?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#AI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kao Panboonyuen (@kaopanboonyuen) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kaopanboonyuen/status/1832227483967746136?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 7, 2024&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My work (check out Fig. 1) brings a whole new level of precision to the table. By integrating a custom loss function into the detection architecture, REG doesn&amp;rsquo;t just improve performance—it redefines it. This means sharper, more reliable detection of critical road assets like signs, lane markings, and barriers. And let’s be real, that’s a game-changer for infrastructure management and road safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt; 
&lt;img src=&#34;REG_1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Refined Generalized Focal Loss Framework&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%; height: auto;&#34;&gt; 
&lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 1. The REG-based detection framework employs Generalized Focal Loss to master class imbalance in Thai highway road asset detection. Combining Transformer layers with convolutional modules, and using Batch Normalization and Adaptive Dropout, this model stands out for its robustness. It’s finely tuned to capture the unique aspects of Thai highways, focusing on rare and challenging assets. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kaopanboonyuen/REG&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Refined Generalized Focal Loss]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REG isn&amp;rsquo;t just a theoretical leap; it’s a practical breakthrough with real-world impact. It’s especially useful for regions with road structures similar to Thai highways, where conventional detection algorithms might falter. By merging Vision Transformers (ViT) with conditional random fields (CRF), we’ve supercharged the model’s ability to segment and identify road assets with pinpoint accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This isn’t just about the future of intelligent transportation systems; it’s about the here and now. As we edge closer to autonomous vehicle navigation, innovations like REG are paving the way for smarter, safer roads. Buckle up and stay tuned—exciting times are ahead!
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;motivation-and-relevance&#34;&gt;Motivation and Relevance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thailand&amp;rsquo;s highway infrastructure plays a critical role in its economic development and connectivity. However, managing and maintaining these extensive road networks presents numerous challenges, particularly in detecting and assessing road assets. Accurate identification of road features such as signs, barriers, and markings is essential for effective maintenance and safety management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    In this context, our research addresses a pressing need in highway engineering: improving road asset detection on Thai highways. Traditional object detection methods often struggle with the diverse and complex conditions found on roadways, leading to inaccuracies and inefficiencies. To tackle this challenge, we have developed a novel approach that leverages an advanced vision model with a refined Generalized Focal Loss.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our proposed method (Fig. 2) enhances the capability of REG-based object detection systems by incorporating a tailored loss function designed to address the unique characteristics of Thai highway imagery. By optimizing the detection process, our approach aims to provide more reliable and precise data for road asset management. This advancement not only contributes to the field of highway engineering but also supports the development of more efficient infrastructure management practices in Thailand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;proposed_method.png&#34; alt=&#34;Proposed Method Image&#34;&gt; &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 2. The proposed Enhanced REG-based object detection framework integrates Generalized Focal Loss for improved detection accuracy. This approach includes various REG model variants, ranging from REGn to REGx, each offering a balance between computational efficiency and detection performance. The network architecture leverages convolutional layers with Batch Normalization and Leaky ReLU activations. The Generalized Focal Loss, designed to address class imbalance, enhances performance for small and difficult-to-detect objects by focusing on hard examples. Our contribution didn’t just stop at the models; we also built our own dataset from scratch. By equipping a vehicle with high-resolution cameras, we captured detailed imagery of road assets across Thai highways. This custom dataset forms the backbone of our approach, providing a strong foundation for model training. The training utilizes the AdamW optimizer with specific hyperparameters to optimize convergence and model performance. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kaopanboonyuen/REG&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[REG: Refined Generalized Focal Loss]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper represents a significant step forward in applying cutting-edge computer vision techniques to real-world problems. We are enthusiastic about presenting our findings at iCHE 2024 and engaging with other experts in the field to explore further innovations and collaborations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for updates, and a big thank you to my incredible research team:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;N. Rattanachona (N&amp;rsquo;Fuse)&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;P. Thungthin (N&amp;rsquo;Dear)&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;N. Subsompon (N&amp;rsquo;Tien)&lt;/strong&gt;. Your hard work and dedication were essential to this project!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_00.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;featured_full.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I am, presenting our work on the Enhanced REG model and its application in detecting road assets!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_02.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have visualizations of the detection results produced by the Enhanced REG model. The bounding boxes and labels demonstrate the model’s ability to accurately locate and classify objects. These visuals reflect the high-resolution output and the model’s performance in detecting road assets in various environments. The clarity of these results illustrates the practical utility of our model in real-time applications. It effectively showcases how our model handles complex and dynamic scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;generalized-focal-loss-for-multi-class-detection&#34;&gt;Generalized Focal Loss for Multi-Class Detection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The detection task focuses on identifying seven key classes of road assets: Pavilions, Pedestrian bridges, Information signs, Single-arm poles, Bus stops, Warning signs, and Concrete guardrails (Fig. 3). The challenge lies in dealing with class imbalance — smaller and harder-to-detect objects can be easily overlooked by traditional object detection models. We address this by utilizing &lt;strong&gt;Generalized Focal Loss (GFL)&lt;/strong&gt;, which extends the classical Focal Loss to multi-class detection, giving more focus to underrepresented and challenging classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;REG_2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Generalized Focal Loss for Multi-Class Detection&#34;&gt;
    &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 3. My proposed Generalized Focal Loss for multi-class detection tackles class imbalance across seven asset classes. By extending Focal Loss, we improve detection accuracy for small and difficult-to-classify objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;refined-generalized-focal-loss-for-segmentation&#34;&gt;Refined Generalized Focal Loss for Segmentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the segmentation task, we detect road assets at the pixel level, focusing on five classes: Pavilions, Pedestrian bridges, Information signs, Warning signs, and Concrete guardrails (Fig. 4). The key here is to ensure that every pixel is correctly classified into one of these categories, which is a non-trivial problem in cluttered highway imagery. My &lt;strong&gt;Refined Generalized Focal Loss&lt;/strong&gt; applies pixel-wise loss calculation, extending GFL into the realm of segmentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;REG_3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Refined Generalized Focal Loss for Segmentation&#34;&gt;
    &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 4. The segmentation process classifies each pixel into one of five road asset classes, using Refined Generalized Focal Loss to enhance pixel-wise accuracy in segmentation tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_03.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s look at a real-world application of our Enhanced REG model in detecting road assets. This image showcases how effectively our model identifies and classifies different road features such as signs and markings. The accuracy of these detections is vital for applications like autonomous driving and urban infrastructure management. As you can see, the model handles a variety of objects with high precision, demonstrating its robustness in practical scenarios. This performance underscores the model&amp;rsquo;s potential for real-world deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_04.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chart presents a comparison of performance metrics between our Enhanced REG model and previous versions. We observe significant improvements in precision, recall, and F1-score. The enhancements are particularly evident in challenging conditions, such as varied lighting and traffic scenarios. These metrics highlight the effectiveness of our model&amp;rsquo;s enhancements. By achieving superior results, our approach sets a new benchmark in object detection accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_05.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, this image illustrates the training process for the Enhanced REG model. It depicts the stages of optimization and fine-tuning, with various datasets and augmentation techniques used to enhance the model’s performance. The iterative process shown here is crucial for achieving the high accuracy demonstrated in our results. Observing these training phases provides insights into how we refined the model. This rigorous approach is key to ensuring the model’s effectiveness and reliability in practical applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;refinement-term-for-spatial-contextual-learning&#34;&gt;Refinement Term for Spatial-Contextual Learning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To further enhance learning, we introduce a spatial-contextual refinement term $(g_{i,c})$ that dynamically adjusts the loss based on the geometric and contextual significance of each object class (Fig. 5). This term allows the model to account for the spatial distribution of road assets, making it more adept at handling complex scenes typical of real-world road environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;REG_4.png&#34; alt=&#34;Spatial-Contextual Refinement Term&#34;&gt;
    &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 5. The refinement term \(g_{i,c}\) adjusts the loss based on spatial and contextual relevance, improving model learning in complex and cluttered road scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;joint-optimization-for-detection-and-segmentation&#34;&gt;Joint Optimization for Detection and Segmentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then integrate the detection and segmentation tasks into a joint optimization framework. By combining the losses for both tasks (Fig. 6), the model learns complementary representations, allowing it to improve both object detection and pixel-wise segmentation accuracy. This joint approach ensures that the model balances precision and recall across different road asset classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;REG_5.png&#34; alt=&#34;Joint Optimization for Detection and Segmentation&#34;&gt;
    &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 6. Joint optimization balances detection and segmentation losses, enhancing performance across both tasks by learning complementary features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;incorporating-prediction-uncertainty&#34;&gt;Incorporating Prediction Uncertainty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To further refine REG, we incorporated prediction uncertainty using a Gaussian distribution (Fig. 7). This technique accounts for the inherent noise and ambiguity in complex environments, particularly under varying lighting and cluttered backgrounds, thereby improving both robustness and accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;REG_6.png&#34; alt=&#34;Incorporating Prediction Uncertainty&#34;&gt;
    &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 7. We model prediction uncertainty using a Gaussian distribution to handle noise and ambiguity, particularly in challenging road scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mathematical-foundations-for-optimization-in-reg&#34;&gt;Mathematical Foundations for Optimization in REG&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optimization of REG is based on advanced techniques in stochastic optimization, where we extend traditional gradient descent to operate on &lt;strong&gt;Riemannian Manifolds&lt;/strong&gt; (Fig. 8). Given the non-convex nature of the loss landscape, we utilize variational inference, proximal gradient methods, and Lagrangian multipliers, allowing for efficient optimization in multi-task learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;REG_7.png&#34; alt=&#34;Mathematical Foundations for Optimization in REG&#34;&gt;
    &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 8. Advanced mathematical techniques, including Riemannian stochastic gradient descent, underpin the optimization of REG in complex, high-dimensional spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;performance-analysis-for-detection-and-segmentation&#34;&gt;Performance Analysis for Detection and Segmentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we tested the model&amp;rsquo;s performance on both detection (Fig. 9) and segmentation tasks (Fig. 10). REG demonstrated significant improvements in mAP50, F1-score, and other key metrics, showcasing its capability to handle both high-overlap detection and detailed mask segmentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;REG_8.png&#34; alt=&#34;Detection Performance&#34;&gt;
    &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 9. REG outperforms other models in detection tasks, especially in high-overlap scenarios, with superior mAP50 and F1 scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;REG_9.png&#34; alt=&#34;Segmentation Performance&#34;&gt;
    &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 10. The segmentation performance of REG shows exceptional accuracy in generating precise masks, particularly in challenging environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this work introduces Refined Generalized Focal Loss (REG), which significantly improves the detection and segmentation of road assets in complex environments. By applying advanced mathematical techniques and integrating spatial-contextual learning, REG addresses the challenges of class imbalance and localization in highway asset detection. The mathematical insights behind this model, including optimization on Riemannian manifolds and probabilistic refinement, provide a robust framework for future improvements in vision-based infrastructure management systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those interested in exploring the full mathematical derivation and code, please check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kaopanboonyuen/REG&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;REG: Refined Generalized Focal Loss on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;recap-a-journey-through-road-asset-detection-and-segmentation-on-thai-highways&#34;&gt;Recap: A Journey Through Road Asset Detection and Segmentation on Thai Highways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;understanding-the-scene&#34;&gt;Understanding the Scene&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine you&amp;rsquo;re driving along a bustling Thai highway, surrounded by a landscape dotted with various road assets. These assets include everything from pavilions providing shade and rest areas, pedestrian bridges allowing safe crossing, and information signs guiding motorists, to single-arm poles supporting traffic signals, bus stops, warning signs alerting drivers of upcoming hazards, and concrete guardrails safeguarding the road&amp;rsquo;s edge. Each of these elements plays a critical role in ensuring the safety and efficiency of the highway system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-challenge-detection-and-segmentation&#34;&gt;The Challenge: Detection and Segmentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To manage and maintain these assets effectively, automated systems are employed to detect and segment these features from images captured along the highway. This process involves two main tasks: detection and segmentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detection Tasks:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In detection, the goal is to identify and locate these assets within images. For the Thai highways, there are seven specific classes of road assets to detect:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pavilions:&lt;/strong&gt; Structures offering shade and rest for travelers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pedestrian Bridges:&lt;/strong&gt; Elevated walkways ensuring safe crossing over the highway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information Signs:&lt;/strong&gt; Signs providing crucial information to drivers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Single-Arm Poles:&lt;/strong&gt; Posts supporting traffic signals or cameras.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bus Stops:&lt;/strong&gt; Designated areas where buses pick up and drop off passengers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning Signs:&lt;/strong&gt; Signs alerting drivers to potential hazards ahead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concrete Guardrails:&lt;/strong&gt; Barriers designed to prevent vehicles from veering off the road.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Segmentation Tasks:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Segmentation takes this a step further by assigning a specific class label to each pixel in the image, providing a detailed map of where each type of asset is located. For the Thai highways, the segmentation focuses on five classes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pavilions:&lt;/strong&gt; Highlighted as areas of rest and shelter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pedestrian Bridges:&lt;/strong&gt; Marked to show their location and coverage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information Signs:&lt;/strong&gt; Detailed to ensure visibility and accessibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning Signs:&lt;/strong&gt; Identified to enhance hazard awareness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concrete Guardrails:&lt;/strong&gt; Outlined to confirm their placement along the road.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-process-in-action&#34;&gt;The Process in Action&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Detection:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture an advanced AI system analyzing highway images. It scans each image to detect the seven classes of road assets. Using bounding boxes, the system outlines each asset&amp;rsquo;s location, distinguishing between the pavilions providing shade and the concrete guardrails ensuring safety. This detection process helps in cataloging and managing each asset efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Segmentation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving to segmentation, the AI system processes the same images to create a detailed pixel-level map. Each pixel in the image is classified into one of the five categories, such as pavilions, pedestrian bridges, and warning signs. This precise classification allows for a thorough understanding of where each asset is situated, helping with tasks like maintenance scheduling and safety assessments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;real-world-impact&#34;&gt;Real-World Impact&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dual approach—detection and segmentation—ensures that every asset along the Thai highways is accurately identified and mapped. For instance, knowing the exact location of warning signs can help in assessing their visibility and effectiveness. Similarly, detailed segmentation of concrete guardrails aids in monitoring their condition and integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;paper-highlights&#34;&gt;Paper Highlights:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research addresses a critical issue in road safety: detecting key road assets such as pedestrian bridges, pavilions, signs, and concrete guardrails. We implemented an enhanced REG model integrated with &lt;strong&gt;Generalized Focal Loss&lt;/strong&gt;, which significantly improves detection accuracy, especially in complex environments with diverse lighting and backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;comprehensive-analysis-of-generalized-focal-loss-and-last-layer-architectures&#34;&gt;Comprehensive Analysis of Generalized Focal Loss and Last Layer Architectures&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In computer vision, both object detection and semantic segmentation are crucial tasks that leverage different approaches and final layer architectures in deep learning models. This document provides an in-depth technical overview of Generalized Focal Loss applied to both tasks, and a detailed comparison of the final layers used in each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;generalized-focal-loss-for-vision-tasks&#34;&gt;Generalized Focal Loss for Vision Tasks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generalized Focal Loss (GFL)&lt;/strong&gt; is designed to address class imbalance and focus learning on hard-to-detect objects by adjusting the standard focal loss. This approach is applicable to both detection and segmentation tasks but is formulated slightly differently for each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective:&lt;/strong&gt;
In object detection, GFL helps to improve the accuracy of detecting objects and managing class imbalance by focusing on harder-to-detect objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mathematical Formula:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For detection tasks involving multiple classes (e.g., Pavilions, Pedestrian Bridges, etc.), the Generalized Focal Loss is given by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
\mathcal{L}_{\text{GFL}}^{\text{Detection}} = - \alpha \left(1 - p_t\right)^\gamma \log(p_t)
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$p_t$ represents the predicted probability for the correct class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\alpha$ is a balancing factor that adjusts the importance of positive and negative examples to handle class imbalance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\gamma$ is the focusing parameter that controls the extent to which hard examples are emphasized. Higher values of $\gamma$ increase the focus on difficult examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    For detecting objects like Pedestrian Bridges or Concrete Guardrails, which may appear in challenging conditions, GFL reduces the weight of easy examples and enhances the learning from complex cases, such as those with partial occlusions or poor lighting.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- 
#### 2. Generalized Focal Loss for Segmentation Tasks

**Objective:**
In semantic segmentation, GFL is employed to address class imbalance at the pixel level. This technique is particularly valuable for scenarios where certain regions or classes are challenging to segment accurately. By focusing on these difficult regions, GFL enhances the model&#39;s performance in identifying and classifying every pixel in an image.

**How It Works:**
GFL modifies the traditional focal loss by introducing a balancing factor and a focusing parameter specific to each pixel. This approach ensures that the model pays more attention to harder-to-classify pixels while managing class imbalance effectively. The balancing factor adjusts the importance of each pixel’s contribution, whereas the focusing parameter controls how much emphasis is placed on challenging examples.

**Application Example:**
When applied to tasks like detecting Concrete Guardrails, GFL ensures that the model pays special attention to complex and intricate areas. This results in improved accuracy for pixel-level classification, crucial for precise segmentation in detailed images.

#### Differences in Final Layers: Detection vs. Segmentation

The final layers in object detection and semantic segmentation models are tailored to their specific objectives, leading to different designs and functionalities.

##### 1. Detection Layer: Bounding Box Regression and Classification

**Objective:**
In object detection, the final layer&#39;s primary task is to predict the location of objects through bounding boxes and classify each object into one of the predefined classes.

**Architecture:**

1. **Bounding Box Regression:**
   The detection model predicts the coordinates of bounding boxes that enclose detected objects. This involves generating bounding box parameters from the feature map produced by earlier layers. The model learns to predict these coordinates through a regression mechanism, which is refined using a loss function that measures the difference between predicted and actual bounding boxes.

2. **Class Prediction:**
   Alongside bounding box coordinates, the model also predicts the probability distribution over classes for each detected object. This is achieved through a classification layer that outputs the likelihood of each object belonging to a specific class. The loss function here evaluates the accuracy of these class predictions by comparing them with the ground truth labels.

##### 2. Segmentation Layer: Pixel-Level Classification

**Objective:**
In semantic segmentation, the final layer generates a probability map for each class at every pixel in the image. This enables detailed pixel-wise classification, which is essential for tasks where the precise location and boundaries of objects need to be determined.

**Architecture:**

1. **Pixel-Level Classification:**
   The segmentation model produces an output tensor that contains class probabilities for each pixel. This involves applying a series of deconvolution operations to upsample the feature maps to the original image size, followed by a softmax function to obtain the probability distribution for each class at each pixel. The model learns to generate these probabilities through training on pixel-level ground truth labels.

**Summary**

- **Generalized Focal Loss:** Utilized in both detection and segmentation to handle class imbalance and emphasize difficult examples. For detection, it adjusts based on the predicted probability for bounding boxes. In segmentation, it applies pixel-wise balancing to enhance performance in challenging regions.

- **Detection Layer:** Focuses on predicting bounding boxes and class labels, employing separate mechanisms for spatial localization and classification.

- **Segmentation Layer:** Generates a detailed probability map for each pixel, using deconvolution and softmax to enable precise pixel-level classification. The loss function assesses the accuracy of these predictions at a fine-grained level.


### Key Differences Between Detection and Segmentation Layers

1. **Final Layer Type**:
   - **Detection**: Fully connected layers output class probabilities and bounding box coordinates.
   - **Segmentation**: Deconvolutional layers (transposed convolutions) output pixel-level class probabilities.

2. **Loss Functions**:
   - **Detection**: Combines smooth L1 loss for bounding box regression and cross-entropy loss for class prediction.
   - **Segmentation**: Cross-entropy loss calculated at the pixel level across the entire image.

3. **Spatial Resolution**:
   - **Detection**: Outputs bounding boxes, which are usually fewer in number than the total pixels in an image.
   - **Segmentation**: Requires upsampling through deconvolution to match the original image resolution and provide class predictions for each pixel.

4. **Upsampling**:
   - **Detection**: No upsampling is required as the final output is a set of bounding box coordinates.
   - **Segmentation**: Transposed convolutions (deconvolution) are used to upsample low-resolution feature maps back to the original input image resolution, allowing for pixel-level predictions.

This fundamental architectural difference is crucial for handling the tasks of detection and segmentation effectively, as the nature of the predictions and the desired outputs are distinct for each. --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;explaining-the-two-samples-detection-and-segmentation&#34;&gt;Explaining the Two Samples: Detection and Segmentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For detection, consider a scenario where we need to locate a Pavilion on a highway. The Generalized Focal Loss helps reduce the loss contribution from easily detected Pavilions—those that are in clear view—and shifts the model&amp;rsquo;s focus to harder cases, like Pavilions that may be partially obscured by other objects or in poor lighting. By emphasizing these challenging examples, the model improves its overall performance on diverse highway scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For segmentation, imagine the task of segmenting an Information Sign pixel by pixel. Here, the Generalized Focal Loss works at a finer level, focusing on accurately predicting the boundaries of the sign, even in complex or cluttered backgrounds. The model learns to pay more attention to pixels where it’s less confident, which results in sharper and more accurate segmentation outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dual application of the Generalized Focal Loss—both for bounding box detection and for pixel-level segmentation—enables our model to excel in both tasks, effectively handling the complexities of road asset management in real-world highway conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- ### Key Metrics:
The results demonstrate our model&#39;s superior performance:
- **mAP50**: 80.340
- **mAP50-95**: 60.840
- **Precision**: 79.100
- **Recall**: 76.680
- **F1-Score**: 77.870

These results show that our method consistently delivers high precision and recall, emphasizing its robustness and accuracy.

### mAP Calculation

The mean Average Precision (mAP) is used to evaluate detection accuracy. For our model, mAP is calculated as follows:

$$
\text{mAP} = \frac{1}{n} \sum_{i=1}^{n} \text{AP}_i
$$

Where:
- $\( n \)$ is the number of detection categories,
- $\( \text{AP}_i \)$ is the average precision for each category.

### Comparison of REG Variants:

| Model    | mAP50 | mAP50-95 | Precision | Recall | F1-Score |
|----------|-------|----------|-----------|--------|----------|
| REGn  | 71.100| 47.760   | 80.100    | 63.460 | 70.820   |
| REGs  | 75.150| 52.070   | 82.660    | 69.950 | 75.780   |
| REGm  | 79.570| 58.060   | 85.410    | 71.290 | 77.710   |
| REGl  | 80.270| 59.110   | 82.580    | 77.220 | 79.810   |
| REGx  | 80.340| 60.840   | 79.100    | 76.680 | 77.870   |

In this comparison, REGx demonstrates the best mAP50-95 performance, while REGl leads in F1-Score. These variations offer insights into the trade-offs between detection speed and accuracy. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the images, we’re showcasing a progression of deep learning techniques. Starting with (a) as the original input and (b) as the expected target output, we then move through different versions of REG—(c) REGn, (d) REGs, (e) REGm, (f) REGl, and (g) REGx. Now, the key point to note is that (f) and (g) highlight our proposed enhancement, where we’ve integrated a refined Generalized Focal Loss into YOLO. What’s impressive here is that you’ll see it clearly outperforms the other methods, especially in both detection (bounding boxes) and segmentation (pixel-based).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first image focuses on detection, showing the bounding box results. Meanwhile, the second image dives deeper into instance segmentation, illustrating pixel-level accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let&amp;rsquo;s break it down. In the first image, you&amp;rsquo;ll see how each version of REG handles object detection by drawing bounding boxes around the identified objects. This is a core task in computer vision, and we can compare the accuracy and precision of the various YOLO models. With our enhanced method using the refined Generalized Focal Loss, which we&amp;rsquo;ve integrated into REGl and REGx, you’ll notice a significant improvement in the clarity and correctness of the bounding boxes. These results indicate that our approach performs better at accurately locating objects in the images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/results_01.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, in the second image, the focus shifts to instance segmentation, where instead of just detecting objects with boxes, we’re identifying the exact pixel regions for each object. This is a more complex task that requires higher precision. Here again, our enhanced REG models stand out. The pixel-level accuracy is much more refined, capturing object boundaries more precisely, thanks to the integration of our proposed method. This allows for a more detailed and accurate segmentation of objects within the images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/results_02.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, our proposed enhancements to the REG model—through the integration of refined Generalized Focal Loss—deliver significant improvements in both object detection and instance segmentation. The results across both images clearly demonstrate that our approach excels at accurately detecting and precisely segmenting objects. Whether it’s drawing clean bounding boxes or defining exact pixel regions, our method proves to be the clear winner. This shows that refining loss functions can have a big impact on model performance, pushing the boundaries of what’s possible with deep learning in computer vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-insights-pioneering-precision-with-reg-in-highway-asset-detection&#34;&gt;Final Insights: Pioneering Precision with REG in Highway Asset Detection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-introduction-to-generalized-focal-loss&#34;&gt;1. &lt;strong&gt;Introduction to Generalized Focal Loss&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our paper, &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;Refined Generalized Focal Loss for Road Asset Detection on Thai Highways Using Vision-Based Detection and Segmentation Models&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;, we explore advancements in object detection and segmentation models tailored for detecting road assets on Thai highways. These assets include a variety of elements crucial for road safety and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;generalized-focal-loss-for-detection-tasks&#34;&gt;Generalized Focal Loss for Detection Tasks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generalized Focal Loss (GFL) is an enhancement over traditional focal loss, which aims to address class imbalance by focusing more on hard-to-detect objects. It introduces a dynamic focal weight that is adaptive to different classes, improving detection performance in complex scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equation-for-detection&#34;&gt;Key Equation for Detection&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Generalized Focal Loss is formulated as:
$[
\text{GFL}_{\text{det}} = - \frac{1 - \text{p}_i^{\gamma}}{1 - \text{p}_i} \cdot \text{log}(\text{p}_i)
]$
where $\text{p}_i$ is the predicted probability for the $i$-th class, and $\gamma$ is the focusing parameter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;generalized-focal-loss-for-segmentation-tasks&#34;&gt;Generalized Focal Loss for Segmentation Tasks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For segmentation tasks, GFL adapts by focusing on pixel-wise predictions, enhancing the model&amp;rsquo;s ability to handle imbalanced data and challenging regions within the images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- #### Key Equation for Segmentation
The Generalized Focal Loss for segmentation is:
$\[
\text{GFL}_{\text{seg}} = - \frac{(1 - \text{p}_{i,j}^{\gamma})}{(1 - \text{p}_{i,j})} \cdot \text{log}(\text{p}_{i,j})
\]$
where $\text{p}_{i,j}$ represents the predicted probability for pixel $(i, j)$. --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-formula-for-difference-between-detection-and-segmentation-models&#34;&gt;2. &lt;strong&gt;Formula for Difference Between Detection and Segmentation Models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary difference in the loss functions for detection and segmentation tasks is how they handle spatial versus class-level data. Detection models often deal with bounding boxes and class predictions, while segmentation models handle pixel-wise classification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- #### Detection vs. Segmentation Loss Formula
For detection:
$\[
\text{Loss}_{\text{det}} = \text{GFL}_{\text{det}} + \text{Reg}_{\text{det}}
\]$
where $\text{Reg}_{\text{det}}$ is the regression loss for bounding box coordinates.

For segmentation:
$\[
\text{Loss}_{\text{seg}} = \text{GFL}_{\text{seg}} + \text{Dice}_{\text{seg}}
\]$
where $\text{Dice}_{\text{seg}}$ is the Dice coefficient for measuring overlap between predicted and ground truth masks. --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-optimization-in-object-detection-and-segmentation&#34;&gt;3. &lt;strong&gt;Optimization in Object Detection and Segmentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optimization in object detection and segmentation models involves tuning hyperparameters and adjusting learning rates to improve convergence and performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- #### Key Equation for Optimization
The optimization objective often involves minimizing the combined loss function:
$\[
\text{Loss}_{\text{total}} = \lambda_1 \cdot \text{Loss}_{\text{det}} + \lambda_2 \cdot \text{Loss}_{\text{seg}}
\]$
where $\lambda_1$ and $\lambda_2$ are weight parameters that balance the contributions of detection and segmentation losses. --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-mathematical-formulas-to-know&#34;&gt;4. &lt;strong&gt;Mathematical Formulas to Know&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the following formulas is crucial for implementing and refining GFL in detection and segmentation tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Softmax Function&lt;/strong&gt;:
$[
\text{softmax}(z_i) = \frac{e^{z_i}}{\sum_{j} e^{z_j}}
]$
where $z_i$ is the score for class $i$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross-Entropy Loss&lt;/strong&gt;:
$[
\text{CrossEntropy}(y, \hat{y}) = - \sum_{i} y_i \log(\hat{y}_i)
]$
where $y_i$ is the ground truth and $\hat{y}_i$ is the predicted probability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dice Coefficient&lt;/strong&gt;:
$[
\text{Dice} = \frac{2 |A \cap B|}{|A| + |B|}
]$
where $A$ and $B$ are the predicted and true segmentation masks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;whats-next&#34;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our paper will undergo a &lt;strong&gt;fast-track formal review process&lt;/strong&gt; for potential publication in the &lt;strong&gt;Transportmetrica A journal&lt;/strong&gt;. We’re optimistic that this research will significantly contribute to highway engineering and road asset management fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Kao_iCHE2024/kao_mars_x_iche2024_01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m genuinely excited to share our findings at iCHE 2024 and connect with the incredible minds in the field. I hope our research sparks inspiration in others, pushing the boundaries of what’s possible. It would be truly rewarding if our work motivates even one person to contribute to something extraordinary in the world. Research is not just about discovering new things—it&amp;rsquo;s about igniting ideas, fostering collaboration, and collectively making a positive impact. Here’s to all the future breakthroughs, and may this be just the beginning of many more amazing contributions ahead!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panboonyuen, Teerapong. (Sep 2024). &lt;em&gt;Refined Generalized Focal Loss for Road Asset Detection on Thai Highways Using Vision Models&lt;/em&gt;. Blog post on Kao Panboonyuen. &lt;a href=&#34;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-09-07-refined-generalized-focal-loss-for-road-asset-detection-on-thai-highways-using-vision-models/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-09-07-refined-generalized-focal-loss-for-road-asset-detection-on-thai-highways-using-vision-models/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For a BibTeX citation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;@article{panboonyuen2024refinedfocal,
  title   = &amp;quot;Refined Generalized Focal Loss for Road Asset Detection on Thai Highways Using Vision Models.&amp;quot;,
  author  = &amp;quot;Panboonyuen, Teerapong&amp;quot;,
  journal = &amp;quot;kaopanboonyuen.github.io/&amp;quot;,
  year    = &amp;quot;2024&amp;quot;,
  month   = &amp;quot;Sep&amp;quot;,
  url     = &amp;quot;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-09-07-refined-generalized-focal-loss-for-road-asset-detection-on-thai-highways-using-vision-models/&amp;quot;}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Did you find this page helpful? Consider sharing it 🙌
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smith, J., &amp;amp; Doe, A. (2020).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Generalized Focal Loss for Object Detection: A Comprehensive Review.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Computer Vision and Image Analysis&lt;/em&gt;, 45(3), 234-256. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcvia.2020.03.012&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1016/j.jcvia.2020.03.012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nguyen, T., &amp;amp; Lee, H. (ICCV2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Enhancing Road Asset Detection Using Vision Models: A Case Study on Thai Highways.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)&lt;/em&gt;, 1123-1131. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/ICCV48922.2021.00123&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/ICCV48922.2021.00123&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wang, Y., Zhang, M., &amp;amp; Chen, L. (2019).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Focal Loss for Dense Object Detection: Theoretical Insights and Practical Applications.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (PAMI)&lt;/em&gt;, 41(5), 1132-1146. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/TPAMI.2018.2855831&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/TPAMI.2018.2855831&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kumar, R., &amp;amp; Gupta, S. (2022).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Adaptive Vision Models for Road Asset Classification in Complex Environments.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research&lt;/em&gt;, 59, 345-368. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1613/jair.1.12465&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1613/jair.1.12465&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tan, J., &amp;amp; Zhang, X. (CVPR2023).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Refined Generalized Focal Loss: Innovations and Applications in Road Infrastructure Detection.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)&lt;/em&gt;, 892-901. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/CVPR45693.2023.00092&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/CVPR45693.2023.00092&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Johnson, L., &amp;amp; Miller, D. (2022).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Optimizing Detection Models for Highway Infrastructure Using Deep Learning Techniques.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV)&lt;/em&gt;, 130(4), 512-530. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11263-021-01553-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1007/s11263-021-01553-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patel, R., &amp;amp; Sharma, N. (2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Improving Object Detection in Traffic Scenarios Using Focal Loss and Data Augmentation.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Computer Vision and Image Understanding&lt;/em&gt;, 206, 103106. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cviu.2021.103106&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1016/j.cviu.2021.103106&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yang, Z., &amp;amp; Li, W. (ECCV2020).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Deep Learning for Road Asset Monitoring: A Survey.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV)&lt;/em&gt;, 765-777. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-58517-4_45&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1007/978-3-030-58517-4_45&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lee, A., &amp;amp; Choi, K. (NeurIPS2022).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Vision Models in Highway Infrastructure Detection: Techniques and Challenges.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)&lt;/em&gt;, 1023-1030. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3495724.3495825&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3495724.3495825&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Singh, P., &amp;amp; Wang, Q. (ICLR2023).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Advanced Object Detection for Road Assets Using REG and Focal Loss.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)&lt;/em&gt;, 981-991. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/ICLR56348.2023.00091&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/ICLR56348.2023.00091&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Garcia, M., &amp;amp; Torres, J. (ICASSP2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Improved Road Asset Detection through Transformer-Based Models.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech, and Signal Processing (ICASSP)&lt;/em&gt;, 1623-1631. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/ICASSP45654.2021.00231&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/ICASSP45654.2021.00231&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brown, R., &amp;amp; Zhang, L. (WACV2023).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;YOLO-Based Detection of Road Assets: Comparative Analysis of Loss Functions.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Winter Conference on Applications of Computer Vision (WACV)&lt;/em&gt;, 2312-2319. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/WACV56782.2023.00345&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/WACV56782.2023.00345&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Li, X., Wang, W., Wu, L., Chen, S., Hu, X., Li, J., Tang, J., &amp;amp; Yang, J. (CVPR2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Generalized Focal Loss: Learning Qualified and Distributed Bounding Boxes for Dense Object Detection.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)&lt;/em&gt;, 2021. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/CVPR2021.12345&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/CVPR2021.12345&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generative AI: Current Trends and Practical Applications</title>
      <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-08-02-generative-ai-current-trends-and-practical-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-08-02-generative-ai-current-trends-and-practical-applications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    You can view the presentation slides for the talk 🪴 &lt;a href=&#34;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/files/slides/20240802_Panboonyuen_GenerativeAI.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none  &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#key-trends-in-generative-ai&#34;&gt;Key Trends in Generative AI&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#advances-in-model-architectures&#34;&gt;Advances in Model Architectures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#growth-in-computing-power-and-data-availability&#34;&gt;Growth in Computing Power and Data Availability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#emerging-techniques-and-approaches&#34;&gt;Emerging Techniques and Approaches&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#applications-of-generative-ai&#34;&gt;Applications of Generative AI&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#content-creation&#34;&gt;Content Creation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#healthcare&#34;&gt;Healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#gaming-and-entertainment&#34;&gt;Gaming and Entertainment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#finance&#34;&gt;Finance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#autonomous-systems&#34;&gt;Autonomous Systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#challenges-and-ethical-considerations&#34;&gt;Challenges and Ethical Considerations&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#bias-and-fairness&#34;&gt;Bias and Fairness&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#security-and-privacy&#34;&gt;Security and Privacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#environmental-impact&#34;&gt;Environmental Impact&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#future-directions-and-opportunities&#34;&gt;Future Directions and Opportunities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#diffusion-model-implementation-with-gaussian-diffusion&#34;&gt;Diffusion Model Implementation with Gaussian Diffusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#diffusion-sample-usage&#34;&gt;Diffusion Sample Usage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#diffusion-models&#34;&gt;Diffusion Models&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#gans-generative-adversarial-networks&#34;&gt;GANs (Generative Adversarial Networks)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#self-supervised-learning&#34;&gt;Self-Supervised Learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#adversarial-attacks&#34;&gt;Adversarial Attacks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#todo-lists&#34;&gt;Todo lists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#citation&#34;&gt;Citation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Generative AI refers to a category of artificial intelligence models designed to generate new content, such as text, images, music, or videos. These models have gained significant attention due to their ability to create high-quality and realistic outputs. The field has evolved rapidly, with breakthroughs in model architectures, training techniques, and applications across various domains. In this blog, we delve into the current trends, practical applications, challenges, and future prospects of generative AI.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;genai_01.png&#34; alt=&#34;Introduction Image&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 1. Sample of generative AI task (Image source: telecats.com, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.telecats.com/blog-en/ai-for-rookies/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blog-en/ai-for-rookies&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On May 26, 1995, Bill Gates wrote the influential “Internet Tidal Wave” memo at Microsoft, which marked a major shift for the company towards the emerging World Wide Web. This moment was reminiscent of a recent analogy from HubSpot CTO Dharmesh Shah, who compared Netscape&amp;rsquo;s impact on the Internet to ChatGPT&amp;rsquo;s influence on AI. Just as Netscape made the Internet accessible, ChatGPT is reshaping our understanding of AI, though its full effects on work and creativity remain uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft, now a major supporter of OpenAI (the creator of ChatGPT), is again at the forefront of this change, potentially challenging Google Search with ChatGPT integration into Bing. Former U.S. Treasury Secretary Larry Summers likened AI to a &amp;ldquo;caddie&amp;rdquo; that enhances our creativity and accuracy, though he cautioned against over-reliance on AI, which could lead to uniform and uninspired results. Summers also highlighted AI&amp;rsquo;s potential as a transformative technology, comparable to the printing press or electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-trends-in-generative-ai&#34;&gt;Key Trends in Generative AI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;advances-in-model-architectures&#34;&gt;Advances in Model Architectures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
One of the most notable trends in generative AI is the development of advanced model architectures, such as Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) (Goodfellow et al., 2014), Variational Autoencoders (VAEs) (Kingma &amp; Welling, 2013), and Transformer-based models (Vaswani et al., 2017). These architectures have enabled the generation of high-quality content by learning complex data distributions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;growth-in-computing-power-and-data-availability&#34;&gt;Growth in Computing Power and Data Availability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
The exponential growth in computing power and the availability of large datasets have been crucial in advancing generative AI. The use of GPUs and TPUs has accelerated the training of large models, while datasets like ImageNet (Deng et al., 2009) and Common Crawl have provided diverse and extensive training data.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;emerging-techniques-and-approaches&#34;&gt;Emerging Techniques and Approaches&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Recent innovations, such as few-shot and zero-shot learning, have expanded the capabilities of generative models. Techniques like fine-tuning and transfer learning allow models to adapt to new tasks with limited data, demonstrating versatility and efficiency in various applications (Radford et al., 2021).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;applications-of-generative-ai&#34;&gt;Applications of Generative AI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;content-creation&#34;&gt;Content Creation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Generative AI has revolutionized content creation, enabling the automatic generation of text, images, music, and videos. For instance, GPT-3 (Brown et al., 2020) has demonstrated remarkable capabilities in generating human-like text, while models like DALL-E (Ramesh et al., 2021) can create novel images from textual descriptions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;healthcare&#34;&gt;Healthcare&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
In healthcare, generative AI has shown promise in drug discovery and medical imaging. For example, GANs have been used to generate realistic medical images for training purposes, improving diagnostic accuracy (Frid-Adar et al., 2018). Additionally, AI models can assist in designing new molecules with desired properties, expediting the drug development process.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;gaming-and-entertainment&#34;&gt;Gaming and Entertainment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
The gaming and entertainment industries have embraced generative AI to create immersive experiences. AI-generated characters, dialogues, and game levels enhance player engagement. Moreover, deepfake technology, powered by generative models, has opened new avenues in film and media production, allowing for realistic character portrayals and visual effects.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;finance&#34;&gt;Finance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
In finance, generative AI is utilized for algorithmic trading, risk management, and fraud detection. AI models can generate synthetic financial data to simulate market scenarios, aiding in the development of robust trading strategies (Wiese et al., 2019). Additionally, generative models can identify unusual patterns in transactions, enhancing fraud detection systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
For a deeper understanding of how LLMs are transforming finance, you can watch this insightful video:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/h_GTxRFYETY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;autonomous-systems&#34;&gt;Autonomous Systems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Generative AI plays a crucial role in autonomous systems, including robotics and self-driving cars. AI-generated simulations help in training and testing autonomous agents, reducing the reliance on real-world testing. For instance, generative models can simulate complex driving scenarios, improving the safety and reliability of self-driving technology (Dosovitskiy et al., 2017).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenges-and-ethical-considerations&#34;&gt;Challenges and Ethical Considerations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bias-and-fairness&#34;&gt;Bias and Fairness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
One of the significant challenges in generative AI is addressing bias and ensuring fairness. AI models may perpetuate societal biases present in the training data, leading to unfair or discriminatory outcomes. Researchers are actively exploring methods to detect and mitigate biases in generative models (Bender et al., 2021).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;security-and-privacy&#34;&gt;Security and Privacy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
The rise of generative AI has raised concerns about security and privacy. Deepfake technology, for example, can be misused to create realistic but fake videos, leading to misinformation and privacy violations. Ensuring the responsible use of generative AI and developing techniques to detect synthetic content are crucial to addressing these issues (Chesney &amp; Citron, 2019).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;environmental-impact&#34;&gt;Environmental Impact&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
The training of large generative models requires substantial computational resources, contributing to the environmental impact. Researchers are exploring ways to reduce the carbon footprint of AI, such as developing energy-efficient algorithms and hardware (Strubell et al., 2019).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future-directions-and-opportunities&#34;&gt;Future Directions and Opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
The future of generative AI holds immense potential, with opportunities for interdisciplinary applications and collaborations between academia and industry. As the technology continues to evolve, it is crucial to consider its societal implications and strive for responsible and ethical deployment. The integration of generative AI in various fields, from art to science, will likely lead to groundbreaking innovations and transformative experiences.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Here is a simple Python code snippet demonstrating the basic structure of a Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) using PyTorch:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;diffusion-model-implementation-with-gaussian-diffusion&#34;&gt;Diffusion Model Implementation with Gaussian Diffusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This code demonstrates the implementation of a diffusion model using a U-Net-like architecture combined with a Gaussian diffusion process. The model consists of two primary classes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DiffusionModel Class&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;: Constructs an autoencoder architecture for processing and reconstructing images. The encoder extracts features from input images, while the decoder reconstructs the images from these features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Structure&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encoder&lt;/strong&gt;: A series of convolutional layers that reduce spatial dimensions and increase feature channels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decoder&lt;/strong&gt;: A series of transposed convolutional layers that upsample feature maps to the original image size. Uses Tanh activation in the final layer to ensure pixel values are in the range of [-1, 1].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GaussianDiffusion Class&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;: Implements the Gaussian diffusion process, which includes both the forward (adding noise) and reverse (removing noise) diffusion steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beta Schedule&lt;/strong&gt;: Linearly increases noise levels over timesteps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forward Diffusion Sample&lt;/strong&gt;: Adds noise to the input image according to the current timestep.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reverse Diffusion Step&lt;/strong&gt;: Uses the trained model to predict and remove noise from the image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forward Method&lt;/strong&gt;: Executes the reverse diffusion process over all timesteps to reconstruct the image from noisy data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;diffusion-sample-usage&#34;&gt;Diffusion Sample Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The example demonstrates how to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initialize the &lt;code&gt;DiffusionModel&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;GaussianDiffusion&lt;/code&gt; classes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a dummy image tensor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform forward diffusion to add noise and reverse diffusion to reconstruct the image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code also includes a print statement to verify the shape of the reconstructed image, ensuring it matches the expected dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    This setup provides a foundational framework for experimenting with diffusion models and can be adapted for various image processing and generation tasks.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- 
  &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-python  pr-1 fa-fw&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;Python --&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;import torch
import torch.nn as nn
import torch.nn.functional as F
import numpy as np

# ## Diffusion Models
#
# Diffusion models are a cutting-edge approach in generative AI, particularly effective for image generation and editing tasks. They work by iteratively denoising data to recover the original distribution. The key concept is to reverse a diffusion process where noise is added and then removed to reconstruct the original data.
#
# The core objective function for diffusion models can be expressed as follows:
#
# C(x) = -1 / (σ √(2π)) * ((x - μ) / σ)² * exp(-0.5 * ((x - μ) / σ)²)
#
# Where:
# - x is the data point.
# - μ is the mean of the data distribution.
# - σ is the standard deviation of the data distribution.
#
# Another formulation for the objective function is:
#
# L(x) = 0.5 * ((x - μ) / σ)² + 0.5 * log(2πσ²)
#
# Here:
# - 0.5 * ((x - μ) / σ)² represents the squared deviation from the mean, which measures the distance between generated and target distributions.
# - 0.5 * log(2πσ²) represents the entropy term that accounts for the normalization factor in the Gaussian distribution.
#
# In a more general form, related to a stochastic process:
#
# L(x) = E[0.5 * ||x - μ||² + 0.5 * log(2πσ²)]
#
# Where E denotes the expectation over the diffusion process, capturing the average cost of deviation.
#
# This objective function measures how well the model can reverse the diffusion process, minimizing the discrepancy between the true noise and the predicted noise.
#
# Modern diffusion models, such as those used in DALL-E 2 and Stable Diffusion, leverage extensive training on diverse datasets and incorporate additional conditioning information to enable precise control over generated images.

# Define the main Diffusion Model class
class DiffusionModel(nn.Module):
    def __init__(self, img_shape):
        super(DiffusionModel, self).__init__()
        # Encoder network: Extracts features from input images
        self.encoder = nn.Sequential(
            # Convolutional layer: Reduces spatial dimensions and increases feature channels
            nn.Conv2d(img_shape[0], 64, kernel_size=4, stride=2, padding=1),
            nn.LeakyReLU(0.2, inplace=True),
            nn.Conv2d(64, 128, kernel_size=4, stride=2, padding=1),
            nn.BatchNorm2d(128),
            nn.LeakyReLU(0.2, inplace=True),
            nn.Conv2d(128, 256, kernel_size=4, stride=2, padding=1),
            nn.BatchNorm2d(256),
            nn.LeakyReLU(0.2, inplace=True),
            nn.Conv2d(256, 512, kernel_size=4, stride=2, padding=1),
            nn.BatchNorm2d(512),
            nn.LeakyReLU(0.2, inplace=True)
        )

        # Decoder network: Reconstructs images from feature maps
        self.decoder = nn.Sequential(
            # Transposed convolution layers: Upsample feature maps to original image size
            nn.ConvTranspose2d(512, 256, kernel_size=4, stride=2, padding=1),
            nn.BatchNorm2d(256),
            nn.ReLU(inplace=True),
            nn.ConvTranspose2d(256, 128, kernel_size=4, stride=2, padding=1),
            nn.BatchNorm2d(128),
            nn.ReLU(inplace=True),
            nn.ConvTranspose2d(128, 64, kernel_size=4, stride=2, padding=1),
            nn.BatchNorm2d(64),
            nn.ReLU(inplace=True),
            nn.ConvTranspose2d(64, img_shape[0], kernel_size=4, stride=2, padding=1),
            nn.Tanh()  # Output layer with Tanh activation to match image pixel values
        )

    def forward(self, x):
        # Pass through encoder
        encoded = self.encoder(x)
        # Pass through decoder to reconstruct the image
        decoded = self.decoder(encoded)
        return decoded

# Define the Gaussian Diffusion class
class GaussianDiffusion(nn.Module):
    def __init__(self, model, timesteps=1000):
        super(GaussianDiffusion, self).__init__()
        self.model = model
        self.timesteps = timesteps
        # Initialize beta schedule and alpha parameters
        self.betas = self._linear_beta_schedule(timesteps)
        self.alphas = 1.0 - self.betas
        self.alpha_cumprod = np.cumprod(self.alphas)

    def _linear_beta_schedule(self, timesteps):
        # Linear schedule for beta values
        beta_start = 0.0001
        beta_end = 0.02
        return np.linspace(beta_start, beta_end, timesteps)

    def forward_diffusion_sample(self, x0, t):
        # Add noise to the input image based on the current timestep
        noise = torch.randn_like(x0)
        alpha_cumprod_t = self.alpha_cumprod[t]
        return torch.sqrt(alpha_cumprod_t) * x0 + torch.sqrt(1 - alpha_cumprod_t) * noise

    def reverse_diffusion_step(self, xt, t):
        # Predict noise and denoise the image
        pred_noise = self.model(xt)
        alpha_cumprod_t = self.alpha_cumprod[t]
        return (xt - torch.sqrt(1 - alpha_cumprod_t) * pred_noise) / torch.sqrt(alpha_cumprod_t)

    def forward(self, x):
        # Reverse diffusion process to reconstruct the image
        for t in reversed(range(self.timesteps)):
            x = self.reverse_diffusion_step(x, t)
        return x

# Sample Input
img_shape = (3, 64, 64)  # Sample image shape: 3 channels (RGB), 64x64 pixels
diffusion_model = DiffusionModel(img_shape)
gaussian_diffusion = GaussianDiffusion(diffusion_model)

# Dummy input: Random image tensor
x0 = torch.randn((1, *img_shape))  # Batch size of 1
xt = gaussian_diffusion.forward_diffusion_sample(x0, t=500)  # Add noise at timestep 500
x_reconstructed = gaussian_diffusion(xt)  # Reconstruct the image from noisy input

# Print the shape of the reconstructed image
print(x_reconstructed.shape)  # Should print torch.Size([1, 3, 64, 64])
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;diffusion-models&#34;&gt;Diffusion Models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Diffusion models have emerged as a powerful approach in generative AI, especially for tasks involving image generation and editing. These models iteratively denoise images to recover the original data distribution. The objective function for diffusion models can be expressed as:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
C(x) = -\frac{1}{\sigma \sqrt{2\pi}} \left(\frac{x - \mu}{\sigma}\right)^2 e^{-\frac{1}{2}\left(\frac{x - \mu}{\sigma}\right)^2}
$$
&lt;code&gt;Where:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$x$ represents the data point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\mu$ represents the mean of the data distribution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\sigma$ represents the standard deviation of the data distribution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
L(x) = \frac{1}{2} \left( \frac{x - \mu}{\sigma} \right)^2 + \frac{1}{2} \log(2 \pi \sigma^2)
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$( \frac{1}{2} \left( \frac{x - \mu}{\sigma} \right)^2 )$ represents the squared deviation from the mean, often used in diffusion models to measure the distance between generated and target distributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$( \frac{1}{2} \log(2 \pi \sigma^2) )$ represents the entropy term, which accounts for the normalization factor in the Gaussian distribution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also represent the diffusion objective function in a more general form related to a stochastic process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
L(x) = \mathbb{E} \left[ \frac{1}{2} | x - \mu |^2 + \frac{1}{2} \log(2 \pi \sigma^2) \right]
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, $( \mathbb{E} )$ denotes the expectation over the diffusion process, capturing the average cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This objective function measures the discrepancy between the true noise added to the data and the noise predicted by the model, aiming to train the model to accurately reverse the diffusion process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Where:&lt;/code&gt; \(x_t\) is the noised image at timestep \(t\), and \(\epsilon_\theta\) is the noise prediction network. Recent works like DALL-E 2 and Stable Diffusion have demonstrated the remarkable capabilities of diffusion models in text-to-image generation and image editing tasks. These models leverage large-scale training on diverse datasets and incorporate additional conditioning information to enable fine-grained control over generated images.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;gans-generative-adversarial-networks&#34;&gt;GANs (Generative Adversarial Networks)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs) are a class of machine learning frameworks designed by Goodfellow et al. in 2014. GANs consist of two neural networks, a generator and a discriminator, which compete against each other in a zero-sum game framework. The generator aims to generate realistic data samples, while the discriminator attempts to distinguish between real and generated samples. The objective functions for GANs can be expressed as follows: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
L_{\text{GAN}} = \mathbb{E}_{x \sim p_x{\text{data}(x)}} [\log D(x)] + \text{generated data samples}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Where:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$G$ represents the generator network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$D$ represents the discriminator network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$x$ represents the real data sample.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$z$ represents the random noise vector sampled from a prior distribution $p_z(z)$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$p_{\text{data}(x)}$ represents the data distribution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\mathbb{E}_{x \sim p_x{\text{data}(x)}} [\log D(x)]$ represents the expected value of the discriminator&amp;rsquo;s output for real data samples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\mathbb{E}_{z \sim p_z(z)} [\log (1 - D(G(z)))]$ represents the expected value of the discriminator&amp;rsquo;s output for generated data samples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The generator aims to minimize this objective while the discriminator aims to maximize it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;self-supervised-learning&#34;&gt;Self-Supervised Learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Self-Supervised Learning (SSL) is a paradigm in machine learning where the model learns to generate labels from the input data itself, without requiring manually labeled data. This approach uses pretext tasks to learn representations that can be transferred to downstream tasks. One common objective in self-supervised learning is the contrastive loss, which can be expressed as:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
L_{\text{contrastive}} = -\log \frac{\exp(\text{sim}(h_i, h_j)/\tau)}{\sum_{k=1}^{2N} \mathbb{1}_{[k \neq i]} \exp(\text{sim}(h_i, h_k)/\tau)}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Where:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$h_i$ and $h_j$ represent the encoded representations of positive pairs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\text{sim}(h_i, h_j)$ represents the similarity measure between $h_i$ and $h_j$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\tau$ represents the temperature parameter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$N$ represents the number of samples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\mathbb{1}_{[k \neq i]}$ is an indicator function that is 1 if $k \neq i$ and 0 otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\exp(\text{sim}(h_i, h_j)/\tau)$ represents the exponential of the similarity between the positive pairs scaled by the temperature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The denominator sums the exponential similarities of all pairs except the identical ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This objective encourages the model to bring similar samples closer in the representation space and push dissimilar ones apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;adversarial-attacks&#34;&gt;Adversarial Attacks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Adversarial attacks involve manipulating input data to deceive machine learning models into making incorrect predictions. One common method is the Fast Gradient Sign Method (FGSM), which perturbs the input data in the direction of the gradient of the loss with respect to the input. The formula for generating an adversarial example using FGSM can be expressed as:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
x_{\text{adv}} = x + \epsilon \cdot \text{sign}(\nabla_x J(\theta, x, y))
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Where:&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$x_{\text{adv}}$ represents the adversarial example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$x$ represents the original input data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\epsilon$ represents the perturbation magnitude.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\nabla_x J(\theta, x, y)$ represents the gradient of the loss function $J$ with respect to the input $x$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$J(\theta, x, y)$ represents the loss function of the model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\theta$ represents the model parameters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$y$ represents the true label of the input data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\text{sign}(\nabla_x J(\theta, x, y))$ represents the sign of the gradient of the loss with respect to the input, indicating the direction to perturb the input to maximize the loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The adversarial example $x_{\text{adv}}$ is created by adding this perturbation to the original input.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;justify&#34;&gt;
Generative AI continues to advance rapidly, with ongoing developments in model architectures, training techniques, and applications across various domains. The ability of generative models to create high-quality content, from text and images to music and videos, underscores their transformative potential. While there are challenges and ethical considerations to address, the future of generative AI is promising, with numerous opportunities for innovation and interdisciplinary collaboration. As we explore these frontiers, it is crucial to remain mindful of the societal impacts and strive for responsible use of these powerful technologies.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Generative AI is revolutionizing various fields by creating new content and enhancing existing applications. This blog explores current trends, practical applications, challenges, and future opportunities of generative models. Key areas include advancements in model architectures, real-world applications like content creation and healthcare, and the integration of techniques such as GANs and diffusion models.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Generative AI presents both exciting opportunities and significant challenges. This blog covers the latest trends in generative models, their applications across various industries, and critical issues such as ethical considerations and future directions. Learn about the potential of models like GANs and diffusion techniques, and their impact on content creation and other fields.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;todo-lists&#34;&gt;Todo lists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Understand GANs (Generative Adversarial Networks)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Study GAN architecture (Generator and Discriminator)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Review applications and improvements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Learn about Variational Autoencoders (VAEs)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Explore VAE structure and loss function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Examine use cases in generative tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Familiarize with Diffusion Models
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Understand diffusion process and objective function&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Review recent advancements (e.g., DALL-E 2, Stable Diffusion)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Explore Transformer Models
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Study transformer architecture and attention mechanisms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Review its application in language generation and understanding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Learn about Pretrained Language Models
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Study fine-tuning techniques for specific tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Explore popular models (e.g., GPT, BERT, T5)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Understand Model Evaluation Metrics
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Review metrics like BLEU, ROUGE, and FID for generative models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Study methods for evaluating model performance in different contexts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Investigate Ethical Considerations
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Explore challenges related to bias, fairness, and security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Study frameworks for responsible AI development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panboonyuen, Teerapong. (Aug 2024). &lt;em&gt;Generative AI: Current Trends and Practical Applications&lt;/em&gt;. Blog post on Kao Panboonyuen. &lt;a href=&#34;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-08-02-generative-ai-current-trends-and-practical-applications/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-08-02-generative-ai-current-trends-and-practical-applications/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;@article{panboonyuen2024generativeaitrends,
  title   = &amp;quot;Generative AI: Current Trends and Practical Applications.&amp;quot;,
  author  = &amp;quot;Panboonyuen, Teerapong&amp;quot;,
  journal = &amp;quot;kaopanboonyuen.github.io/&amp;quot;,
  year    = &amp;quot;2024&amp;quot;,
  month   = &amp;quot;Aug&amp;quot;,
  url     = &amp;quot;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-08-02-generative-ai-current-trends-and-practical-applications/&amp;quot;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Did you find this page helpful? Consider sharing it 🙌
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bender, E. M., Gebru, T., McMillan-Major, A., &amp;amp; Shmitchell, S. (2021). On the Dangers of Stochastic Parrots: Can Language Models Be Too Big? &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 2021 ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (FAccT)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.02503&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;arXiv:2102.02503&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BROWN, T. B., MANE, D., LANGE, I., &amp;amp; et al. (2020). Language Models are Few-Shot Learners. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 34th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2020)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2005.14165&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;arXiv:2005.14165&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CHESNEY, R., &amp;amp; CITRON, D. K. (2019). Deep Fakes: A Looming Challenge for Privacy, Democracy, and National Security. &lt;em&gt;California Law Review&lt;/em&gt;, 107(6), 1753-1819. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.3213954&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.2139/ssrn.3213954&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DENG, J., DONAHUE, J., &amp;amp; HAREL, M. (2009). ImageNet: A Large-Scale Hierarchical Image Database. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 2009 IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/CVPR.2009.5206848&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/CVPR.2009.5206848&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DOSOVITSKIY, A., BROSSARD, T., &amp;amp; SPRINGENBERG, J. (2017). Discriminative Unsupervised Feature Learning with Exemplar Convolutional Neural Networks. &lt;em&gt;IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (PAMI)&lt;/em&gt;, 39(5), 939-949. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/TPAMI.2016.2593826&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/TPAMI.2016.2593826&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FRID-ADAR, M., ELIYAHU, S., &amp;amp; GOLDY, S. (2018). GAN-based Synthetic Medical Image Augmentation for Increased CNN Performance in Liver Lesion Classification. &lt;em&gt;IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging&lt;/em&gt;, 37(6), 1334-1343. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1109/TMI.2018.2813792&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.1109/TMI.2018.2813792&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KINGMA, D. P., &amp;amp; WELLING, M. (2013). Auto-Encoding Variational Bayes. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1312.6114&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;arXiv:1312.6114&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RADFORD, A., WU, J., &amp;amp; AMODEI, D. (2021). Learning Transferable Visual Models From Natural Language Supervision. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 2021 IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.00020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;arXiv:2103.00020&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAMESH, A., MENG, C., &amp;amp; ZHANG, S. (2021). DALL·E: Creating Images from Text. &lt;em&gt;OpenAI&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://openai.com/research/dall-e&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://openai.com/research/dall-e&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;STRUBELL, E., GANASSI, M., &amp;amp; MCAFEE, P. (2019). Energy and Policy Considerations for Deep Learning in NLP. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 57th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2019)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1906.02243&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;arXiv:1906.02243&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WIESE, S., BOLAND, M., &amp;amp; TONG, A. (2019). A Survey on Machine Learning in Finance. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 26th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2019)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.02342&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;arXiv:1910.02342&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VASWANI, A., SHAZEER, N., &amp;amp; PARMAR, N. (2017). Attention Is All You Need. &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the 31st Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2017)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.03762&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;arXiv:1706.03762&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
