<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>LULC | Teerapong Panboonyuen</title>
    <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/tag/lulc/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/tag/lulc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>LULC</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2025 Kao Panboonyuen</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/media/icon_hueaa9297dc78a770d45cebdfb81bbca28_1203332_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>LULC</title>
      <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/tag/lulc/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vision–Language Models for Remote Sensing: A New Era of Multimodal Understanding</title>
      <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2025-07-05-visionlanguage-models-for-remote-sensing-a-new-era-of-multimodal-understanding/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2025-07-05-visionlanguage-models-for-remote-sensing-a-new-era-of-multimodal-understanding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, it’s me again, &lt;strong&gt;Kao Panboonyuen&lt;/strong&gt;—welcome back to my blog! 😊 Today, I’m diving into a topic that’s been on my mind a lot lately: the exciting intersection of &lt;strong&gt;Remote Sensing&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Large Language Models (LLMs)&lt;/strong&gt;. As you know, &lt;strong&gt;remote sensing&lt;/strong&gt; is one of the most powerful tools for understanding the Earth’s surface, using &lt;strong&gt;satellite systems&lt;/strong&gt; like &lt;strong&gt;Sentinel-2&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Landsat-8&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;THEOS&lt;/strong&gt; to capture tons of &lt;strong&gt;high-resolution data&lt;/strong&gt;. From monitoring &lt;strong&gt;environmental changes&lt;/strong&gt; to assisting in &lt;strong&gt;urban planning&lt;/strong&gt;, this data has countless applications. But here’s the catch—while we have all this amazing data at our fingertips, its sheer volume and complexity can overwhelm traditional methods of &lt;strong&gt;data classification&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Older algorithms like &lt;strong&gt;Support Vector Machines (SVM)&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Random Forest (RF)&lt;/strong&gt; have done a decent job, but they often struggle to tap into the &lt;strong&gt;deeper semantic meaning&lt;/strong&gt; within the data. They can classify pixels, sure, but they can’t grasp the rich, contextual relationships between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s where &lt;strong&gt;LLMs&lt;/strong&gt; come in! These models, originally built for &lt;strong&gt;natural language processing&lt;/strong&gt;, have the power to &lt;strong&gt;revolutionize remote sensing&lt;/strong&gt; by interpreting and analyzing data on a much deeper level. By &lt;strong&gt;integrating contextual insights&lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;satellite metadata&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;environmental reports&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;LLMs&lt;/strong&gt; can enhance tasks like &lt;strong&gt;LULC (Land Use/Land Cover) classification&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;image analysis&lt;/strong&gt;. The results? Much more accurate and insightful interpretations of satellite imagery, opening up a whole new world of possibilities for &lt;strong&gt;remote sensing applications&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remote sensing&lt;/strong&gt; has become an indispensable tool for gaining detailed insights into the Earth&amp;rsquo;s surface, with satellite systems like &lt;strong&gt;Sentinel-2&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Landsat-8&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;THEOS&lt;/strong&gt; providing an endless stream of &lt;strong&gt;high-resolution data&lt;/strong&gt;. From &lt;strong&gt;environmental monitoring&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;urban planning&lt;/strong&gt;, this data fuels critical applications across a range of sectors. Yet, the vast volume and &lt;strong&gt;complexity&lt;/strong&gt; of satellite imagery can present a significant challenge. Traditional methods of &lt;strong&gt;data classification&lt;/strong&gt;, such as &lt;strong&gt;Support Vector Machines (SVM)&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Random Forest (RF)&lt;/strong&gt;, have delivered valuable results but are often unable to capture the full &lt;strong&gt;semantic richness&lt;/strong&gt; embedded within this data. They excel at processing large datasets, but struggle when tasked with understanding the deeper, contextual relationships between the elements within these images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter the era of &lt;strong&gt;Large Language Models (LLMs)&lt;/strong&gt;, which are revolutionizing the way we process and interpret remote sensing data. Originally designed to understand and generate &lt;strong&gt;human-like language&lt;/strong&gt;, LLMs have demonstrated an incredible capacity to enhance &lt;strong&gt;data analysis&lt;/strong&gt; by integrating &lt;strong&gt;contextual information&lt;/strong&gt; from multiple sources—such as &lt;strong&gt;environmental reports&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;satellite metadata&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;geospatial context&lt;/strong&gt;. This ability to handle &lt;strong&gt;multimodal data&lt;/strong&gt; opens up new avenues for more accurate &lt;strong&gt;Land Use/Land Cover (LULC)&lt;/strong&gt; classification and &lt;strong&gt;image interpretation&lt;/strong&gt;, driving improvements in remote sensing applications that were once constrained by traditional algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent Twitter post, &lt;strong&gt;Lilian Weng&lt;/strong&gt; excitedly shared the launch of &lt;strong&gt;Thinking Machines Lab&lt;/strong&gt;, a cutting-edge AI research and product company dedicated to pushing the boundaries of &lt;strong&gt;multimodal understanding&lt;/strong&gt;. As she mentions, the lab is home to some of the brightest minds behind innovations like &lt;strong&gt;ChatGPT&lt;/strong&gt;. Their focus on multimodal AI is particularly relevant to the work being done with &lt;strong&gt;Vision–Language Models (VLMs)&lt;/strong&gt;, which are rapidly transforming how we analyze remote sensing data. Just like &lt;strong&gt;Thinking Machines Lab&lt;/strong&gt; aims to integrate various AI disciplines to achieve greater synergy, &lt;strong&gt;VLMs&lt;/strong&gt; are creating new possibilities for understanding &lt;strong&gt;satellite imagery&lt;/strong&gt; by combining &lt;strong&gt;computer vision&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;natural language processing&lt;/strong&gt;. This shift not only enhances our ability to interpret complex data but also paves the way for more intuitive, human-like understanding of the world around us. To learn more about &lt;strong&gt;Thinking Machines Lab&lt;/strong&gt; and their vision, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://thinkingmachines.ai&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Thinking Machines&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;This is something we have been cooking together for a few months and I&amp;#39;m very excited to announce it today.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thinking Machines Lab is my next adventure and I&amp;#39;m feeling very proud and lucky to start it with a group of talented colleagues. Learn more about our vision at… &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/eKQYvuwurB&#34;&gt;https://t.co/eKQYvuwurB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Lilian Weng (@lilianweng) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lilianweng/status/1891922794402939092?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 18, 2025&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;visionlanguage-models-vlms&#34;&gt;Vision–Language Models (VLMs)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, &lt;strong&gt;Vision–Language Models (VLMs)&lt;/strong&gt; have emerged as a groundbreaking tool in remote sensing, particularly in enhancing the interpretation of satellite imagery. These models merge visual data with linguistic understanding, offering a more holistic approach to analyzing complex remote sensing data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most exciting developments in this area is how VLMs can enrich traditional remote sensing datasets. While traditional datasets often rely purely on raw imagery, VLMs leverage contextual relationships between visual inputs and textual data, providing more nuanced insights. The integration of textual descriptions or geospatial metadata alongside imagery allows for a deeper understanding of land use, land cover changes, and other environmental factors. This ability is showcased in a comparative visualization, where you can clearly see how VLM datasets offer richer and more detailed information than traditional methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power of VLMs lies not just in their ability to process images, but also in their proficiency at handling a variety of tasks simultaneously. For instance, these models can assist in tasks such as object detection, classification, and even scene understanding. A representation of these tasks reveals just how versatile VLMs can be across different domains of remote sensing. From simple land cover classification to more complex tasks like environmental monitoring, VLMs are equipped to tackle them all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we dig deeper into the structure of VLMs, it becomes clear that they come in various forms, each designed to handle specific challenges in remote sensing. For example, &lt;strong&gt;contrastive models&lt;/strong&gt; focus on matching images with descriptive text, while &lt;strong&gt;conversational models&lt;/strong&gt; are more dynamic, enabling interactive querying and real-time interpretation of satellite imagery. This distinction in architecture allows VLMs to be adaptable to a wide range of applications, from automatic image captioning to detailed environmental analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to their core functionality, enhancement techniques are often employed to refine VLM performance. Some layers of the model are &lt;strong&gt;fine-tuned&lt;/strong&gt; to improve precision, while others are kept &lt;strong&gt;frozen&lt;/strong&gt; to preserve previously learned features. These techniques are crucial for boosting model efficiency without overfitting, ensuring that VLMs can be effectively applied to large-scale remote sensing tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growing interest in VLMs is also reflected in the increasing number of academic publications dedicated to this field. Over the past few years, the volume of research in the intersection of VLMs and remote sensing has surged, reflecting the potential of these models to transform how we understand and analyze satellite data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_SAMPLE_RS_LLMS_00001.png&#34; alt=&#34;Comparison of traditional and VLM datasets in remote sensing&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 1: A comparative analysis between traditional and Vision–Language Model (VLM) datasets in the context of remote sensing. Traditional datasets typically rely on isolated visual data (such as satellite images) for classification and interpretation, often limited by the scope of raw pixel-based information. In contrast, VLM datasets integrate both visual and textual modalities, incorporating contextual information like environmental reports, geospatial metadata, and textual descriptions. This hybrid approach enhances the model&#39;s ability to capture complex relationships and nuanced patterns in satellite imagery, improving classification accuracy and providing richer insights for land use/land cover (LULC) analysis and other remote sensing tasks. (Image source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/17/1/162&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MDPI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As shown in the visual comparison above, the shift from traditional datasets to VLM datasets in remote sensing is not just about increasing data volume but about enhancing the depth and accuracy of the insights derived from satellite imagery. The traditional approach provides basic visual data, while VLM datasets incorporate semantic understanding, making it easier to identify patterns, trends, and anomalies that would otherwise go unnoticed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the remarkable aspects of VLMs is their ability to handle a wide variety of tasks. The tasks shown in the figure below range from simple image classification to more complex objectives such as environmental change detection and land use forecasting. With their integrated vision and language capabilities, VLMs can extract much more detailed and contextually relevant information from imagery than traditional models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_SAMPLE_RS_LLMS_00002.png&#34; alt=&#34;Representative tasks of Vision–Language Models in remote sensing&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 2: A detailed overview of representative tasks handled by Vision–Language Models (VLMs) in remote sensing. VLMs bridge the gap between visual and textual data, enabling them to perform complex multimodal tasks such as image captioning, object detection, and semantic segmentation. These models can analyze high-resolution satellite imagery while leveraging textual data like geospatial metadata, environmental descriptions, and sensor reports to provide a more comprehensive understanding of the landscape. For instance, VLMs are increasingly used in land use/land cover (LULC) classification, change detection, and disaster monitoring, offering enhanced performance over traditional methods by incorporating contextual information to reduce ambiguity. (Image source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/17/1/162&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MDPI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flexibility of VLMs in handling such diverse tasks opens new possibilities in remote sensing, where the understanding of both imagery and textual data is vital for accurate analysis. The synergy between vision and language also plays a key role in making sense of complex environmental data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we look at the underlying architecture of VLMs, it’s clear that they are not a one-size-fits-all solution. Models can either use a &lt;strong&gt;contrastive approach&lt;/strong&gt;, focusing on pairing images with descriptions, or a more &lt;strong&gt;conversational approach&lt;/strong&gt;, which allows for interactive querying of imagery. This flexibility is key for the adaptability of VLMs in real-world applications, whether it&amp;rsquo;s for immediate analysis or long-term monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_SAMPLE_RS_LLMS_00004.png&#34; alt=&#34;Architecture of contrastive and conversational Vision–Language Models&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 3: A detailed breakdown of the architectures for contrastive (left) and conversational (right) Vision–Language Models (VLMs), two key paradigms that drive the integration of visual and textual data in remote sensing. The contrastive architecture utilizes a dual encoder framework where image features and textual features are independently extracted and then aligned in a common multimodal space. This design is particularly effective in tasks requiring fine-grained matching, such as image captioning and cross-modal retrieval. On the other hand, the conversational architecture builds upon the contrastive model by introducing a dialogue-based approach, enabling more dynamic interactions between the visual content and natural language queries. This makes conversational models ideal for applications like interactive mapping, question-answering systems, and real-time disaster monitoring, where context and user input are continually evolving. The figure contrasts these two architectures to highlight how they each excel in different aspects of remote sensing tasks. (Image source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/17/1/162&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MDPI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This versatility in architecture makes VLMs well-suited to tackle a broad spectrum of remote sensing tasks. Whether you need to extract simple patterns or generate more detailed, context-rich analyses, the choice of model architecture significantly impacts the output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, as with all machine learning models, VLMs require careful optimization to ensure they perform at their best. Enhancement techniques, like &lt;strong&gt;fine-tuning&lt;/strong&gt; certain layers and keeping others &lt;strong&gt;frozen&lt;/strong&gt;, are used to strike the right balance between model complexity and efficiency. These strategies help to refine VLMs for specific tasks, improving accuracy and minimizing computational overhead, as illustrated in the figure below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_SAMPLE_RS_LLMS_00005.png&#34; alt=&#34;Enhancement techniques in Vision–Language Models&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 4: A visual representation of the various enhancement techniques employed in Vision–Language Models (VLMs) to improve their performance and accuracy in remote sensing applications. These techniques include fine-tuning and transfer learning, where pre-trained models are further optimized to adapt to specific domain tasks. The diagram showcases the interplay between frozen and fine-tuned layers, with fine-tuning denoted by the fire icon, representing the model&#39;s ability to adapt to new data, and frozen layers indicated by the snowflake icon, maintaining the stability of pre-existing knowledge. By employing these enhancement strategies, VLMs can effectively improve their ability to handle complex tasks such as LULC classification, disaster detection, and environmental monitoring, all while reducing the risk of overfitting and improving generalization to unseen datasets. (Image source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/17/1/162&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MDPI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These enhancement techniques are essential for optimizing VLMs for large-scale remote sensing tasks, enabling them to extract meaningful insights from satellite imagery without becoming too computationally expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growing body of research on VLMs reflects the increasing recognition of their potential in remote sensing. A recent graph shows a clear upward trend in the number of publications on the use of VLMs in this field, indicating that the scientific community is embracing these models as a valuable tool for future research and applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_SAMPLE_RS_LLMS_00003.png&#34; alt=&#34;Examples of tasks handled by Vision–Language Models (VLMs) in remote sensing&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 5: A comprehensive breakdown of the various complex tasks addressed by Vision–Language Models (VLMs) in the field of remote sensing. By combining both visual data (such as satellite imagery) and textual information (like metadata, sensor reports, and geospatial documentation), VLMs are revolutionizing the way we approach tasks like image captioning, land use/land cover (LULC) classification, and change detection. The integration of these modalities allows VLMs to not only process raw visual content but also to infer meaningful insights by incorporating contextual understanding. This synergy of vision and language empowers VLMs to enhance disaster monitoring, environmental analysis, and climate change studies, offering unprecedented accuracy and interpretability in remote sensing applications. (Image source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/17/1/162&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MDPI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the field of VLMs in remote sensing continues to expand, it’s clear that these models will play a pivotal role in transforming how we analyze and interpret satellite imagery, driving new innovations and methodologies in environmental monitoring and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;understanding-large-language-models-llms&#34;&gt;Understanding Large Language Models (LLMs)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLMs, such as GPT-4, are trained on massive corpora of text data, enabling them to grasp the intricacies of human language. However, their capacity to process sequential information isn&amp;rsquo;t limited to just text. Recent studies have shown that LLMs, when appropriately adapted, can learn to analyze non-textual data types, such as images, by incorporating their textual understanding into feature extraction processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In remote sensing, LLMs can be adapted to the following roles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Textual Contextualization&lt;/strong&gt;: LLMs can process and generate insights from external textual datasets, such as reports, maps, and metadata, which provide contextual information for satellite images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enhanced Feature Extraction&lt;/strong&gt;: By understanding the relationships between textual data and imagery, LLMs help derive semantic features that are difficult for traditional image processing algorithms to capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mathematically, LLMs utilize attention mechanisms, specifically the Transformer architecture, which enables them to weigh different parts of the input sequence with varying importance. This attention mechanism can be defined as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
\text{Attention}(Q, K, V) = \text{softmax}\left(\frac{QK^T}{\sqrt{d_k}}\right) V
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$Q$ represents the query (textual or image features),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$K$ represents the key (spatial or contextual attributes),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$V$ is the value (output features or attention score),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$d_k$ is the dimensionality of the key vectors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process helps in focusing on relevant parts of the data, whether it be image patches or semantic concepts, which improves classification accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;llms-in-lulc-classification&#34;&gt;LLMs in LULC Classification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Land Use/Land Cover (LULC) classification is a fundamental task in remote sensing, involving the categorization of land regions into distinct types based on satellite imagery. Traditional methods, while powerful, often overlook the contextual understanding of features that can be provided by external data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To improve accuracy, we employ a hybrid model that combines Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) with LLMs. The CNN extracts spatial features from satellite images, while the LLM extracts contextual information from external sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integration of LLMs in the LULC classification process can be broken down into the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Collection&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High-resolution imagery is collected from platforms like Sentinel-2, Landsat-8, and THEOS, which offer multispectral and multisource data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preprocessing&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Images are corrected for atmospheric distortion and radiometrically normalized using techniques such as the Dark Object Subtraction (DOS) method to reduce atmospheric scattering.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feature Extraction&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CNN architectures (such as ResNet-50 or EfficientNet) are applied to extract spatial features from satellite imagery. Simultaneously, large environmental corpora, such as land use reports, are processed by LLMs to extract contextual knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hybrid Model Training&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The CNN-derived spatial features and the LLM-derived contextual features are concatenated and fed into a fully connected neural network for final classification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Classification and Validation&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After training, the model is applied to a test set of images. Metrics such as accuracy, precision, recall, and F1-score are used to evaluate the performance. A typical validation equation for precision and recall is given as:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
\text{Precision} = \frac{TP}{TP + FP}, \quad \text{Recall} = \frac{TP}{TP + FN}
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$TP$ is the number of true positives,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$FP$ is the number of false positives,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$FN$ is the number of false negatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;case-study-sentinel-2-imagery-classification&#34;&gt;Case Study: Sentinel-2 Imagery Classification&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To demonstrate the power of LLMs in enhancing LULC classification, we present a case study using Sentinel-2 imagery. Sentinel-2 provides multispectral images at a spatial resolution of up to 10 meters, allowing for detailed land cover analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-collection-and-preprocessing&#34;&gt;Data Collection and Preprocessing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sentinel-2 images covering a diverse region were downloaded and preprocessed to correct atmospheric effects. Image reflectance values were normalized using the FLAASH (Fast Line-of-sight Atmospheric Analysis of Spectral Hypercubes) method to improve data consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;feature-extraction&#34;&gt;Feature Extraction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We applied ResNet-50 for feature extraction from the raw satellite imagery. For contextual understanding, an LLM (such as GPT-4) was fed with environmental reports and metadata related to the region to extract textual features that provide insights into land use policies, climate conditions, and historical land usage trends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hybrid-model-training&#34;&gt;Hybrid Model Training&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extracted features from both the CNN and LLM were combined into a hybrid model, trained using a multi-class cross-entropy loss function. The model achieved an accuracy improvement of 12% compared to traditional classification methods that relied solely on CNNs or SVMs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;challenges-and-future-prospects&#34;&gt;Challenges and Future Prospects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the integration of LLMs in remote sensing holds promise, several challenges remain. These include the need for large, high-quality datasets for training LLMs, the computational cost of training hybrid models, and the difficulty in obtaining ground truth data for validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future research will focus on refining these models and exploring new techniques such as semi-supervised learning and transfer learning to further enhance performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we continue to observe the rise of &lt;strong&gt;Vision–Language Models (VLMs)&lt;/strong&gt; in remote sensing, one notable trend is the growing body of academic work that explores their capabilities. The figure below demonstrates the increasing number of publications on VLMs in the field of remote sensing, reflecting the broad interest and potential for these models to shape the future of satellite imagery analysis. As the research landscape evolves, we can expect even more innovative approaches and applications to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_SAMPLE_RS_LLMS_00006.png&#34; alt=&#34;Number of publications for Vision–Language Models (VLMs) in remote sensing&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 6: A comprehensive visualization of the growing number of publications focused on Vision–Language Models (VLMs) in the field of remote sensing. This trend underscores the increasing interest in the integration of multimodal learning (combining visual and textual data) to enhance the accuracy and efficiency of remote sensing tasks, such as LULC classification, change detection, and disaster response. The upward trajectory of VLM research reflects both the advancements in AI model architecture and the expanding applicability of these models to complex, real-world geospatial challenges. The data presented here highlights the growing recognition of VLMs as a key technology in modern remote sensing workflows. (Image source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/17/1/162&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MDPI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the pursuit of enhancing model performance, &lt;strong&gt;LLaVA (Large Vision-and-Language Model)&lt;/strong&gt; is one of the newer architectures that’s making waves in the remote sensing community. This innovative model is designed to seamlessly integrate both vision and language modalities, providing a rich foundation for sophisticated interpretations of satellite imagery. As illustrated below, LLaVA offers a more intuitive and interactive way of combining imagery with text, making it especially valuable in applications like land use classification, environmental monitoring, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_SAMPLE_RS_LLMS_00007.png&#34; alt=&#34;An illustration of LLaVA, a Vision–Language Model&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 7: A comprehensive illustration of LLaVA (Large Language and Vision Alignment), an advanced Vision–Language Model (VLM) designed to seamlessly integrate visual and textual information. LLaVA enables fine-grained multimodal reasoning, allowing it to process complex datasets from diverse sources such as satellite imagery and environmental reports. By leveraging large-scale pre-trained models, LLaVA enhances performance in tasks like remote sensing and image classification through the fusion of visual cues and textual context. This approach has shown significant promise in enhancing model interpretability, particularly in applications where both visual and linguistic insights are crucial. (Image source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mdpi.com/2072-4292/17/1/162&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MDPI&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the heart of many VLMs is the &lt;strong&gt;Transformer architecture&lt;/strong&gt;, which has revolutionized how models process sequences of data, whether they be text, images, or both. The transformer model&amp;rsquo;s ability to handle long-range dependencies in data has made it the backbone of cutting-edge models like GPT, BERT, and, of course, Vision Transformers (ViTs). A diagram illustrating the Transformer architecture highlights how it efficiently handles both visual and linguistic data, making it a crucial component for tasks that require understanding of complex, multimodal data sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_SAMPLE_RS_LLMS_00008.png&#34; alt=&#34;Illustration of Transformer architecture, a cornerstone of modern deep learning models&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 8: A comprehensive illustration of the Transformer architecture, a breakthrough deep learning model that revolutionized sequence-based data processing. This architecture leverages self-attention mechanisms to capture long-range dependencies in data, which makes it highly effective in a wide range of tasks, including natural language processing and computer vision. It serves as the foundational model for Vision Transformers (ViTs) and Vision–Language Models (VLMs) in remote sensing. (Image source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2017/file/3f5ee243547dee91fbd053c1c4a845aa-Paper.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;NeurIPS 2017&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vision Transformers (ViTs) are one of the latest and most powerful iterations of the Transformer model, specifically designed to handle image data. Unlike traditional convolutional neural networks (CNNs), ViTs treat image patches as sequences, enabling them to capture both local and global features more effectively. The figure below offers an overview of the Vision Transformer model and its ability to process large-scale imagery data. Its application in remote sensing has shown promise, particularly for high-resolution satellite imagery classification, where understanding fine-grained patterns is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;img/KAO_SAMPLE_RS_LLMS_00009.png&#34; alt=&#34;Model overview of Vision Transformer&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Figure 9: Detailed model overview of the Vision Transformer (ViT), a cutting-edge deep learning architecture that has transformed the way image data is processed. Unlike traditional convolutional neural networks (CNNs), ViT divides an image into fixed-size patches and processes them as sequences, allowing the model to capture both local and global dependencies in an image simultaneously. This unique approach has led to impressive performance in high-resolution satellite image classification and other remote sensing tasks, making it a key model in the field of Vision–Language Models (VLMs). ViT&#39;s scalability to handle large-scale image data have made it indispensable for remote sensing applications. (Image source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2010.11929/1000&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of LLMs with traditional remote sensing techniques offers a significant improvement in the accuracy and contextual understanding of LULC classification tasks. By leveraging both spatial feature extraction from CNNs and semantic contextualization from LLMs, remote sensing models can achieve more precise and meaningful results. This approach opens new avenues for analyzing satellite imagery and provides deeper insights into Earth’s surface processes, aiding in applications ranging from environmental monitoring to urban planning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integration of &lt;strong&gt;Vision–Language Models (VLMs)&lt;/strong&gt; into remote sensing is more than just a technological leap; it represents a paradigm shift in how we interpret and interact with satellite imagery. By combining the power of both visual data and linguistic context, VLMs open up new frontiers in &lt;strong&gt;land use/land cover (LULC) classification&lt;/strong&gt;, environmental monitoring, and countless other applications. The innovative capabilities of these models are not just theoretical—they are already being realized in practical, real-world scenarios, as evidenced by the growing body of research and the increasing number of publications in the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results we&amp;rsquo;ve explored here demonstrate that &lt;strong&gt;VLMs&lt;/strong&gt; are not just another tool—they are a powerful bridge that connects the language of the Earth’s landscapes to the language of machine learning. With their ability to process complex multimodal data, they offer unprecedented accuracy, scalability, and efficiency in satellite data analysis. The rise of models like &lt;strong&gt;LLaVA&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;Vision Transformer (ViT)&lt;/strong&gt; exemplify this potential, illustrating how cutting-edge architecture is pushing the boundaries of what’s possible in &lt;strong&gt;remote sensing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes these models truly remarkable is their ability to not only analyze individual images but also to understand the nuanced context within those images. This contextual understanding is where traditional methods fall short, making &lt;strong&gt;VLMs&lt;/strong&gt; a game-changer. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s distinguishing between subtle changes in land cover, detecting environmental anomalies, or improving the precision of automated classification, these models offer a level of sophistication that will likely define the future of remote sensing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we look ahead, it’s clear that &lt;strong&gt;VLMs&lt;/strong&gt; are poised to drive significant advancements in the way we monitor, understand, and protect our planet. The intersection of &lt;strong&gt;AI&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;remote sensing&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;language&lt;/strong&gt; will continue to evolve, opening doors to new research, innovations, and applications. For professionals in the field of remote sensing, the question is no longer whether to adopt &lt;strong&gt;VLMs&lt;/strong&gt;, but how soon and how deeply to integrate them into their workflows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog, we’ve explored the methodologies, models, and real-world implications of integrating &lt;strong&gt;VLMs&lt;/strong&gt; into &lt;strong&gt;remote sensing&lt;/strong&gt;. The insights from this growing area of research suggest that &lt;strong&gt;Vision–Language Models&lt;/strong&gt; will not only enhance the precision and scope of satellite data interpretation but will also unlock new levels of meaning and insight that were previously unattainable. As we continue to refine these models and expand their capabilities, the potential for &lt;strong&gt;VLMs&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;remote sensing&lt;/strong&gt; is limitless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the integration of &lt;strong&gt;Vision–Language Models&lt;/strong&gt; with remote sensing is not just an exciting trend—it is the future of how we will analyze, interpret, and leverage satellite imagery to make better decisions for our planet’s future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s a wrap for today! I hope you found this exploration into &lt;strong&gt;Vision–Language Models&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;remote sensing&lt;/strong&gt; insightful and inspiring. Whether you’re new to the field or a seasoned pro, I’m sure there are a few ideas or &lt;strong&gt;takeaways&lt;/strong&gt; that can spark your next big project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading—until next time, take care and keep pushing the boundaries of knowledge! 🌍&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kao Panboonyuen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panboonyuen, Teerapong. (July 2025). &lt;em&gt;Vision–Language Models for Remote Sensing: A New Era of Multimodal Understanding&lt;/em&gt;. Blog post on Kao Panboonyuen. &lt;a href=&#34;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2025-07-05-visionlanguage-models-for-remote-sensing-a-new-era-of-multimodal-understanding/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2025-07-05-visionlanguage-models-for-remote-sensing-a-new-era-of-multimodal-understanding/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For a BibTeX citation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;@article{panboonyuen2025vlmrsllms,
  title   = &amp;quot;Vision–Language Models for Remote Sensing: A New Era of Multimodal Understanding&amp;quot;,
  author  = &amp;quot;Panboonyuen, Teerapong&amp;quot;,
  journal = &amp;quot;kaopanboonyuen.github.io/&amp;quot;,
  year    = &amp;quot;2025&amp;quot;,
  month   = &amp;quot;Jul&amp;quot;,
  url     = &amp;quot;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2025-07-05-visionlanguage-models-for-remote-sensing-a-new-era-of-multimodal-understanding/&amp;quot;}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Did you find this page helpful? Consider sharing it 🙌
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Fine-Tune and Deploy a Satellite-Specific LLMs Model for Satellite Images</title>
      <link>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-09-09-how-to-fine-tune-and-deploy-a-satellite-specific-llm-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-09-09-how-to-fine-tune-and-deploy-a-satellite-specific-llm-model/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    You can view the presentation slides for the talk 🌎 &lt;a href=&#34;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/files/slides/20240910_Panboonyuen_How_to_Fine_Tune_Satellite_Specific_LLM.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none  &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction-to-large-language-models-llms&#34;&gt;Introduction to Large Language Models (LLMs)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#key-vocabulary&#34;&gt;Key Vocabulary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#architecture-of-llms&#34;&gt;Architecture of LLMs&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#transformer-architecture-formula&#34;&gt;Transformer Architecture Formula&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#training-llms&#34;&gt;Training LLMs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#introduction-to-llms-for-satellite-images&#34;&gt;Introduction to LLMs for Satellite Images&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#exploring-vision-language-models-vlms-to-understand-high-level-features-in-remotely-sensed-images&#34;&gt;Exploring Vision-Language Models (VLMs) to Understand High-Level Features in Remotely Sensed Images&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-makes-vision-language-models-vlms-special&#34;&gt;What Makes Vision-Language Models (VLMs) Special?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#challenges-in-remote-sensing-with-vlms&#34;&gt;Challenges in Remote Sensing with VLMs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#benchmarking-vlms-on-landmark-recognition&#34;&gt;Benchmarking VLMs on Landmark Recognition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#diving-deeper-into-vlms-case-studies-of-landmark-recognition-and-scene-interpretation&#34;&gt;Diving Deeper into VLMs: Case Studies of Landmark Recognition and Scene Interpretation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#overview-of-the-fine-tuning-process&#34;&gt;Overview of the Fine-Tuning Process&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#step-by-step-fine-tuning-of-satgpt-for-satellite-imagery&#34;&gt;Step-by-Step Fine-Tuning of SatGPT for Satellite Imagery&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1-data-preparation&#34;&gt;1. Data Preparation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#2-model-selection&#34;&gt;2. Model Selection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#3-fine-tuning-paradigm&#34;&gt;3. Fine-Tuning Paradigm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#4-model-validation-and-evaluation&#34;&gt;4. Model Validation and Evaluation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#5-export-and-deployment-to-hugging-face&#34;&gt;5. Export and Deployment to Hugging Face&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#additional-concepts&#34;&gt;Additional Concepts&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#formula-for-self-attention-in-rag&#34;&gt;Formula for Self-Attention in RAG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#vision-transformer-vit&#34;&gt;Vision Transformer (ViT)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#full-flow-diagram&#34;&gt;Full Flow Diagram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#quick-thoughts-on-llms-before-we-wrap-up-this-blog&#34;&gt;Quick thoughts on LLMs before we wrap up this blog:&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1-introduction-to-large-language-models-llms-in-remote-sensing&#34;&gt;1. &lt;strong&gt;Introduction to Large Language Models (LLMs) in Remote Sensing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#2-foundation-models-and-their-role-in-llms&#34;&gt;2. &lt;strong&gt;Foundation Models and Their Role in LLMs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#3-training-vs-fine-tuning-vs-pre-trained-models-in-llms&#34;&gt;3. &lt;strong&gt;Training vs Fine-tuning vs Pre-trained Models in LLMs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#4-how-to-train-llms-on-satellite-images&#34;&gt;4. &lt;strong&gt;How to Train LLMs on Satellite Images&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#5-retrieval-augmented-generation-rag-for-satellite-image-analysis&#34;&gt;5. &lt;strong&gt;Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) for Satellite Image Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#6-using-langchain-for-satellite-image-llm-applications&#34;&gt;6. &lt;strong&gt;Using LangChain for Satellite Image LLM Applications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#7-sample-datasets-for-llm-fine-tuning-in-remote-sensing&#34;&gt;7. &lt;strong&gt;Sample Datasets for LLM Fine-Tuning in Remote Sensing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#8-mathematical-foundations-of-attention-mechanisms-in-llms&#34;&gt;8. &lt;strong&gt;Mathematical Foundations of Attention Mechanisms in LLMs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#9-multimodal-llm-architectures-for-satellite-images&#34;&gt;9. &lt;strong&gt;Multimodal LLM Architectures for Satellite Images&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#10-preprocessing-techniques-for-satellite-images-in-llms&#34;&gt;10. &lt;strong&gt;Preprocessing Techniques for Satellite Images in LLMs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#11-handling-illumination-and-atmospheric-effects-in-llms&#34;&gt;11. &lt;strong&gt;Handling Illumination and Atmospheric Effects in LLMs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#12-self-supervised-learning-ssl-for-satellite-image-analysis&#34;&gt;12. &lt;strong&gt;Self-Supervised Learning (SSL) for Satellite Image Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#13-open-source-tools-for-llms-in-satellite-image-analysis&#34;&gt;13. &lt;strong&gt;Open-Source Tools for LLMs in Satellite Image Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#14-fine-tuning-llms-for-specific-satellite-image-tasks&#34;&gt;14. &lt;strong&gt;Fine-Tuning LLMs for Specific Satellite Image Tasks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#15-evaluation-metrics-for-llms-in-remote-sensing&#34;&gt;15. &lt;strong&gt;Evaluation Metrics for LLMs in Remote Sensing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#16-transfer-learning-for-satellite-imagery&#34;&gt;16. &lt;strong&gt;Transfer Learning for Satellite Imagery&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#17-explainability-in-llms-for-remote-sensing-xai&#34;&gt;17. &lt;strong&gt;Explainability in LLMs for Remote Sensing (XAI)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#citation&#34;&gt;Citation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction-to-large-language-models-llms&#34;&gt;Introduction to Large Language Models (LLMs)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Large Language Models (LLMs) are at the forefront of a revolution in Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Natural Language Processing (NLP). These models are not just sophisticated algorithms; they represent a leap forward in how machines understand and generate human language. Leveraging cutting-edge deep learning architectures, such as transformers, LLMs have transformed the landscape of language technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;We&amp;#39;re releasing a preview of OpenAI o1—a new series of AI models designed to spend more time thinking before they respond.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;These models can reason through complex tasks and solve harder problems than previous models in science, coding, and math. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/peKzzKX1bu&#34;&gt;https://t.co/peKzzKX1bu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; OpenAI (@OpenAI) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/OpenAI/status/1834278217626317026?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 12, 2024&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At their essence, LLMs are built on expansive neural networks with billions of parameters. These networks are trained on vast corpora of text data, learning to discern intricate patterns and relationships within language. Through a process known as pre-training, LLMs develop a broad understanding of linguistic structures, context, and semantics. During this phase, they utilize unsupervised learning techniques to predict masked words or sequences, refining their ability to understand and generate coherent text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Curious about fine-tuning a satellite-specific LLM model? 🌍&lt;br&gt;.&lt;br&gt;Dive into my latest blog to learn more: &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/sd25ByzQpJ&#34;&gt;https://t.co/sd25ByzQpJ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/LLM?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#LLM&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Geoscience?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Geoscience&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/SatelliteLLM?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#SatelliteLLM&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/AI?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#AI&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/MachineLearning?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#MachineLearning&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Landsat?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#Landsat&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/geography?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#geography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kao Panboonyuen (@kaopanboonyuen) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kaopanboonyuen/status/1833511803739116039?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 10, 2024&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Following pre-training, LLMs undergo fine-tuning to adapt their general language capabilities to specific tasks or domains. This supervised learning phase involves training the model on a targeted dataset, allowing it to excel in applications such as text generation, translation, sentiment analysis, and question-answering. Techniques like transfer learning and few-shot learning further enhance the model&amp;rsquo;s adaptability, enabling it to generalize from limited examples and perform across various contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deploying LLMs in real-world scenarios involves addressing practical challenges related to computational resources and scalability. These models require substantial processing power and memory, often necessitating the use of advanced hardware like GPUs or TPUs. Despite these demands, the benefits of integrating LLMs into applications—such as chatbots, virtual assistants, content generation, and automated summarization—are profound, offering significant advancements in how machines interact with human language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I will delve into the technical intricacies of LLMs, exploring their architecture, training methodologies, and deployment considerations. Prepare to discover how these powerful AI tools are pushing the boundaries of language technology and shaping the future of machine intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-vocabulary&#34;&gt;Key Vocabulary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some essential terms and acronyms related to LLMs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acronym&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meaning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Artificial Intelligence: The simulation of human intelligence in machines that are programmed to think and learn.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ANN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Artificial Neural Network: A computational model inspired by biological neural networks.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BERT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers: A model for natural language understanding tasks.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CNN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Convolutional Neural Network: Effective for processing grid-like data such as images.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CRF&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Conditional Random Field: A statistical modeling method for structured prediction.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DNN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deep Neural Network: A neural network with multiple layers.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deep Learning: A subset of machine learning with neural networks containing many layers.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GPT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Generative Pre-trained Transformer: A transformer-based model for generating human-like text.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HMM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hidden Markov Model: A model for systems that transition between states with certain probabilities.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LSTM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Long Short-Term Memory: A type of RNN designed to remember long-term dependencies.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LLM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Large Language Model: Trained on vast amounts of text data to understand and generate text.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ML&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Machine Learning: Training algorithms to make predictions based on data.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NLP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Natural Language Processing: The interaction between computers and human language.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RAG&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Retrieval-Augmented Generation: Combines document retrieval with generative models.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RNN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Recurrent Neural Network: Designed for sequential data.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Text-to-Text Transfer Transformer: Converts various tasks into a text-to-text format.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transformer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A model architecture that uses self-attention mechanisms.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ViT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Vision Transformer: A transformer model for image processing.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VQA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Visual Question Answering: Combining vision and language understanding.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VLMs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Vision-Language Models: Close the divide between visual and language comprehension in AI.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;XLNet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;An extension of BERT with permutation-based training.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hugging Face&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Platform for NLP with pre-trained models, datasets, and tools.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transformers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Library for transformer-based models by Hugging Face.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;datasets&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Library for managing datasets, by Hugging Face.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gradio&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Library for creating machine learning demos with simple UIs.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LangChain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Facilitates development using LLMs with tools for managing language-based tasks.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;spaCy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Advanced NLP library in Python.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NLTK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Natural Language Toolkit: Tools for text processing and linguistic analysis.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;StanfordNLP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Library by Stanford University for NLP tasks.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OpenCV&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Library for computer vision tasks.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PyTorch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deep learning framework with tensor computations and automatic differentiation.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TensorFlow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Framework for building and deploying machine learning models.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keras&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;High-level neural networks API running on top of TensorFlow.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fastai&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Simplifies neural network training with PyTorch.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ONNX&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Open Neural Network Exchange format for model transfer between frameworks.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;architecture-of-llms&#34;&gt;Architecture of LLMs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LLMs are built on advanced architectures that often include transformer models. A transformer model utilizes self-attention mechanisms to process input sequences. The core components of a transformer are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encoder&lt;/strong&gt;: Processes the input data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decoder&lt;/strong&gt;: Generates the output sequence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;transformer-architecture-formula&#34;&gt;Transformer Architecture Formula&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key mathematical operation in transformers is the self-attention mechanism, which can be described as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$[ \text{Attention}(Q, K, V) = \text{softmax}\left(\frac{QK^T}{\sqrt{d_k}}\right)V ]$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$( Q )$ is the query matrix,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$( K )$ is the key matrix,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$( V )$ is the value matrix,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$( d_k )$ is the dimensionality of the keys.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;training-llms&#34;&gt;Training LLMs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Training LLMs involves several steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Preparation&lt;/strong&gt;: Collect and preprocess large text corpora.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Model Initialization&lt;/strong&gt;: Start with a pre-trained model or initialize from scratch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training&lt;/strong&gt;: Use gradient descent and backpropagation to minimize the loss function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction-to-llms-for-satellite-images&#34;&gt;Introduction to LLMs for Satellite Images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fine-tuning a Large Language Model (LLM) like SatGPT for satellite imagery involves several critical stages. This process transforms a pre-trained model into a specialized tool capable of analyzing and generating insights from satellite images. This blog post provides a step-by-step guide to fine-tuning and deploying SatGPT, covering each phase in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their 2024 paper, &lt;em&gt;“Good at Captioning, Bad at Counting: Benchmarking GPT-4V on Earth Observation Data”&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17600&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;arXiv:2401.17600&lt;/a&gt;), Zhang and Wang focus on developing a benchmark for Vision-Language Models (VLMs) applied to Earth Observation (EO) data. Their initial framework addresses three main areas: scene understanding, localization and counting, and change detection. To assess VLM performance across these areas, they design evaluations that span various applications, from wildlife conservation to urban monitoring, as illustrated in Figure 1. Their goals are to evaluate existing VLMs, provide insights into effective prompting techniques for EO tasks, and establish a flexible system for ongoing benchmark updates and future VLM evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!-- 
For scene understanding, Zhang and Wang assess how VLMs integrate high-level image information with latent knowledge from language modeling. They use several datasets for this purpose: a new dataset for aerial landmark recognition to test the model’s ability to identify and geolocate U.S. landmarks, the RSICD dataset to evaluate the model’s capability to generate captions for Google Earth images, the BigEarthNet dataset to probe land cover identification in medium-resolution satellite images, and the fMoW-WILDS and PatternNet datasets to assess land use classification in high-resolution satellite images.
 --&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    The paper highlights several challenges and areas for future work. One major challenge is detecting data contamination, which is crucial for maintaining the fairness and effectiveness of benchmarks as VLMs evolve. Additionally, a more detailed analysis of model failures—such as knowledge gaps, reasoning errors, perceptual mistakes, and text misunderstandings—could provide deeper insights into current VLM capabilities. Zhang and Wang also note the static nature of benchmarks as a limitation, suggesting that dynamic updates may be necessary to keep benchmarks relevant and challenging as VLMs advance.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/SatGPT?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;#SatGPT&lt;/a&gt; is an app that lets you talk to satellite imagery.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We&amp;#39;ve got some more work to do before it&amp;#39;s polished, but I&amp;#39;m pretty psyched about the results so far. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Powered by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Element84?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Element84&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/STACspec?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@STACspec&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/LangChainAI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@LangChainAI&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Panel_org?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Panel_org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/HoloViz_org?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@HoloViz_org&lt;/a&gt;, huge thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ivanziogeo?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@ivanziogeo&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MarcSkovMadsen?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@MarcSkovMadsen&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/gO7aZz6w4C&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/gO7aZz6w4C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kevin Lalli (@opticsinspace) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/opticsinspace/status/1670688747552411649?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 19, 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;!-- 
In the domain of localization and counting, Zhang and Wang evaluate whether VLMs can extract detailed information about specific objects and understand their spatial relationships. They create datasets for this purpose, including the DIOR-RSVG dataset to test Referring Expression Comprehension (REC) abilities, where the model localizes objects based on natural language descriptions. Additionally, they use the NEON-Tree, COWC, and xBD datasets to evaluate the counting of small objects like trees, cars, and buildings in aerial and satellite images, and the aerial animal detection dataset to assess the model’s ability to count animals in tilted aerial images.

For change detection, the focus is on evaluating how VLMs track changes over time. Zhang and Wang use a dataset that categorizes buildings by damage levels and presents the data in JSON format, tracking counts before and after damage across various categories.



In the context of image captioning, Zhang and Wang evaluate the ability of instruction-following VLMs to describe aerial or satellite images. Their evaluation uses the RSICD dataset to compare VLM-generated captions with human-annotated examples both qualitatively and quantitatively, assessing how well VLMs describe images at various levels of detail.

For land use and land cover (LULC) classification, Zhang and Wang assess VLMs&#39; performance on multiple-choice classification tasks using datasets like fMoW-WILDS, PatternNet, and BigEarthNet. Their aim is to determine which models excel in zero-shot classification and how image resolution impacts classification accuracy. They find that VLM performance varies based on image resolution, label ambiguity, and granularity. Specifically, GPT-4V shows lower performance in land cover classification compared to specialized models but performs better on certain datasets like fMoW-WILDS and PatternNet. The challenges of ambiguous class labels and limited multi-spectral information in the BigEarthNet dataset also affect GPT-4V&#39;s performance.

Overall, Zhang and Wang’s work underscores the importance of evolving benchmarks and VLM capabilities to address the challenges in EO data applications.

They deliver an in-depth analysis of GPT-4V’s performance across different tasks. Figure 1 illustrates key scenarios and the model’s performance: --&gt;
&lt;!-- 
1. **Location Recognition**  
   **Scenario:** Identify the landmark based on its features, such as its dome and layout.  
   **Example Answer:** The landmark, recognized by its distinctive style and layout, is the Nebraska State Capitol.

2. **Image Captioning**  
   **Scenario:** Generate a one-sentence caption for the provided image.  
   **Example Caption:** An aerial view of an airport terminal, showcasing nearby aircraft, taxiways, and parking areas.

3. **Land Use &amp; Land Cover Classification**  
   **Scenario:** Categorize the image into one of several predefined categories.  
   **Example Classification:** The image is best described as a Shipping Yard.

4. **Object Localization**  
   **Scenario:** Pinpoint the coordinates of a described object in the image.  
   **Example Description:** The gray windmill in the center.  
   **Coordinates:** [233, 383, 376, 542]

5. **Object Counting**  
   **Scenario:** Estimate the number of trees visible in the image.  
   **Count:** 134

6. **Change Detection**  
   **Scenario:** Count buildings in various damage categories and present the data in JSON format.  
   **JSON Format:**  
   ```json
   {
     &#34;count_before&#34;: 75,
     &#34;no_damage&#34;: 2,
     &#34;minor_damage&#34;: 73,
     &#34;major_damage&#34;: 0,
     &#34;destroyed&#34;: 1
   }
   ```

**Performance Metrics:**

- **RefCLIP Score:** Evaluates the model’s performance on reference-based tasks.
- **F1 Score:** Measures the model’s accuracy in classification tasks.
- **Mean IoU:** Assesses the model’s performance in object localization.
- **R2 Score:** Gauges the model’s predictive accuracy across various tasks. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These findings offer valuable insights into GPT-4V’s capabilities and limitations, especially in the context of earth observation data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;sample_apps.png&#34; alt=&#34;Earth observation data&#34;&gt; &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 1. Here are examples of inputs and outputs from various benchmark tasks and how five different VLMs stack up. They’ve included just a snippet of the user prompts and model responses to highlight the key points. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.17600v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Good at captioning, bad at counting]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;exploring-vision-language-models-vlms-to-understand-high-level-features-in-remotely-sensed-images&#34;&gt;Exploring Vision-Language Models (VLMs) to Understand High-Level Features in Remotely Sensed Images&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my recent work, I&amp;rsquo;ve been diving deep into Vision-Language Models (VLMs) to see how well they perform in tasks that require understanding both visual and textual data. With the explosion of AI models that can interpret images and generate coherent, detailed text, it’s become increasingly important to assess these models not just on general benchmarks, but in specific, high-stakes domains like remotely sensed imagery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remotely sensed images, which are collected from satellite or aerial platforms, provide a unique challenge for VLMs. They are dense with data, full of patterns, and often contain complex interactions between natural and man-made objects. The ability of a model to not only caption these images but also understand high-level features—such as differentiating between natural landmarks, infrastructure, and potential environmental changes—can have far-reaching applications in fields like agriculture, urban planning, and disaster response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;img src=&#34;Figure2.png&#34; alt=&#34;VLM Comparison for Benchmark Tasks&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 2. A comparison of inputs and outputs from benchmark tasks using different VLMs. The snippet includes user prompts and model responses, highlighting key areas of model performance.
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.17600v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Good at captioning, bad at counting]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-makes-vision-language-models-vlms-special&#34;&gt;What Makes Vision-Language Models (VLMs) Special?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VLMs operate at the intersection of vision and language, giving them the ability to describe images with textual explanations. This makes them incredibly useful for analyzing and interpreting remote sensing data. In these images, VLMs can recognize patterns, identify important landmarks, and even offer insights into the features present within the scene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while these models excel at captioning tasks—offering detailed and sometimes creative descriptions—they can struggle with more precise tasks like counting objects or recognizing certain functional categories. This is a critical gap that must be addressed, especially in applications where accuracy is paramount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;challenges-in-remote-sensing-with-vlms&#34;&gt;Challenges in Remote Sensing with VLMs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the major challenges I’ve observed while working with VLMs on remotely sensed images is the models&amp;rsquo; difficulty in consistently recognizing high-level features, especially when dealing with complex or less common landmarks. This can lead to a high rate of refusal or incorrect identification in certain categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, a model might easily recognize a natural park or large urban feature, but struggle to identify a specific sports venue or government building. These variances are especially pronounced when analyzing remote imagery, where the perspective and scale can make recognition even more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;benchmarking-vlms-on-landmark-recognition&#34;&gt;Benchmarking VLMs on Landmark Recognition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran some experiments using five different VLMs (GPT-4V, InstructBLIP-TS-XXL, InstructBLIP-Vicuna-13b, LLaVA-v1.5, Qwen-VL-Chat) to see how well they could identify landmarks in a set of remotely sensed images. Below is the summary of the results for landmark recognition accuracy (Table 1) and refusal rate (Table 2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;Table1and2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Table 1 and 2: Landmark Recognition Accuracy and Refusal Rate&#34;&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Table 1: Landmark recognition accuracy by functional category and Table 2: Landmark recognition refusal rate.
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.17600v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Good at captioning, bad at counting]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, there are significant variances in how different models perform across these categories. GPT-4V and InstructBLIP tend to outperform other models in recognizing large, prominent landmarks like natural parks and urban infrastructure. However, there’s still considerable room for improvement, especially when identifying more specific or niche features, like places of worship or government buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;diving-deeper-into-vlms-case-studies-of-landmark-recognition-and-scene-interpretation&#34;&gt;Diving Deeper into VLMs: Case Studies of Landmark Recognition and Scene Interpretation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nuances of how Vision-Language Models (VLMs) understand and interpret images can be observed more clearly in specific examples. Below, I’ve analyzed a few key scenarios where GPT-4V has demonstrated both its strengths and limitations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;visual-recognition-with-architectural-context&#34;&gt;Visual Recognition with Architectural Context&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One fascinating case is GPT-4V’s ability to link visual cues with its knowledge of architecture. In &lt;strong&gt;Figure 3&lt;/strong&gt;, the model successfully identifies a landmark by connecting the architectural style with its vast knowledge base, arriving at the correct answer. This demonstrates its ability to use contextual clues beyond just object recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;img src=&#34;Figure3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Architectural Landmark Identification&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 3. GPT-4V successfully corresponds visual cues with its knowledge about the architectural style of the landmark to arrive at the correct answer.
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.17600v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Good at captioning, bad at counting]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-problem-of-visual-misinterpretation&#34;&gt;The Problem of Visual Misinterpretation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, VLMs aren&amp;rsquo;t infallible. One case where GPT-4V struggled is in the identification of the &lt;strong&gt;Nebraska State Capitol&lt;/strong&gt;. In &lt;strong&gt;Figure 4&lt;/strong&gt;, the model incorrectly eliminates the correct answer due to misidentifying the tower-like structure. This reveals a significant gap in its ability to distinguish more subtle architectural details, leading to incorrect conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;img src=&#34;Figure4.png&#34; alt=&#34;Misidentification of Nebraska State Capitol&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 4. GPT-4V fails to identify the tower-like structure of the Nebraska State Capitol, leading to incorrect elimination.
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.17600v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Good at captioning, bad at counting]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;correct-identification-but-weak-justifications&#34;&gt;Correct Identification but Weak Justifications&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, even when GPT-4V identifies a landmark correctly, it sometimes provides insufficient reasoning. In &lt;strong&gt;Figure 5&lt;/strong&gt;, the model identifies the landmark, but the reasoning lacks depth, which could be a hindrance in scenarios requiring detailed explanations, such as educational or research-oriented applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;img src=&#34;Figure5.png&#34; alt=&#34;Correct Identification but Weak Reasoning&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 5. GPT-4V correctly identifies the landmark but gives insufficient reasoning.
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.17600v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Good at captioning, bad at counting]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;generating-image-captions-for-complex-scenes&#34;&gt;Generating Image Captions for Complex Scenes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting scenario is when the model is tasked with generating captions for complex images. In &lt;strong&gt;Figure 6&lt;/strong&gt;, GPT-4V generates several captions for an airport image. While the captions are coherent, they sometimes miss finer details, like the specific types of airplanes or terminal features, which could be crucial in more technical applications like surveillance or logistics planning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;img src=&#34;Figure6.png&#34; alt=&#34;Airport Caption Generation&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 6. Example captions generated for an airport image.
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.17600v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Good at captioning, bad at counting]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;object-localization-in-remote-sensing&#34;&gt;Object Localization in Remote Sensing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Object localization is another key area where VLMs need to perform exceptionally well. In &lt;strong&gt;Figure 7&lt;/strong&gt;, GPT-4V is tasked with localizing objects in a DIOR-RSVG dataset image. While it performs reasonably well, there are still challenges in precisely identifying and categorizing certain objects, especially in cluttered or low-contrast scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;img src=&#34;Figure7.png&#34; alt=&#34;Object Localization in DIOR-RSVG Dataset&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 7. Example prompt and response for DIOR-RSVG object localization.
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.17600v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Good at captioning, bad at counting]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;detecting-changes-in-xview2-imagery&#34;&gt;Detecting Changes in xView2 Imagery&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in &lt;strong&gt;Figure 8&lt;/strong&gt;, the model is put to the test with change detection using the xView2 dataset, where it must identify changes in infrastructure and the environment. This kind of task is essential in applications like disaster response or urban monitoring, where rapid and accurate assessments can make a significant difference. GPT-4V’s performance is promising, but it still leaves room for improvement, especially in recognizing more subtle changes or those happening over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;img src=&#34;Figure8.png&#34; alt=&#34;Change Detection in xView2 Dataset&#34;&gt; 
  &lt;p style=&#34;font-style: italic; margin-top: 0px;&#34;&gt;Fig. 8. Example prompt and response for xView2 change detection.
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.17600v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;[Good at captioning, bad at counting]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview-of-the-fine-tuning-process&#34;&gt;Overview of the Fine-Tuning Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of fine-tuning and deploying a satellite-specific LLM model involves the following stages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Preparation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Model Selection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fine-Tuning Paradigm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Model Validation and Evaluation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Export and Deployment to Hugging Face&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-by-step-fine-tuning-of-satgpt-for-satellite-imagery&#34;&gt;Step-by-Step Fine-Tuning of SatGPT for Satellite Imagery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-data-preparation&#34;&gt;1. Data Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective&lt;/strong&gt;: Collect, preprocess, and format satellite images and associated textual annotations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collect Satellite Images&lt;/strong&gt;: Obtain satellite images from sources such as commercial providers or public datasets (e.g., Sentinel, Landsat).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annotate Images&lt;/strong&gt;: Label images with relevant information (e.g., land cover types, objects of interest).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preprocess Images&lt;/strong&gt;: Resize and normalize images to match the input requirements of the Vision Transformer (ViT) model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prepare Textual Descriptions&lt;/strong&gt;: Generate textual descriptions or annotations for each image, which will be used for training the text generation component.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;from transformers import ViTFeatureExtractor, GPT2Tokenizer

# Initialize feature extractor and tokenizer
feature_extractor = ViTFeatureExtractor.from_pretrained(&#39;google/vit-base-patch16-224-in21k&#39;)
tokenizer = GPT2Tokenizer.from_pretrained(&#39;gpt2&#39;)

# Sample image and text
image = ... # Load satellite image
text = &amp;quot;This is a description of the satellite image.&amp;quot;

# Prepare inputs
inputs = feature_extractor(images=image, return_tensors=&amp;quot;pt&amp;quot;)
labels = tokenizer(text, return_tensors=&amp;quot;pt&amp;quot;).input_ids
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-model-selection&#34;&gt;2. Model Selection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective&lt;/strong&gt;: Choose an appropriate pre-trained model as the foundation for SatGPT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Options&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision Transformer (ViT)&lt;/strong&gt;: For processing and extracting features from satellite images.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GPT-2 or GPT-3&lt;/strong&gt;: For generating textual descriptions or insights based on image features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;from transformers import GPT2LMHeadModel, ViTModel

# Load pre-trained models
image_model = ViTModel.from_pretrained(&#39;google/vit-base-patch16-224-in21k&#39;)
text_model = GPT2LMHeadModel.from_pretrained(&#39;gpt2&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-fine-tuning-paradigm&#34;&gt;3. Fine-Tuning Paradigm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective&lt;/strong&gt;: Adapt the selected models to work together for the specific task of analyzing satellite imagery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Combine Models&lt;/strong&gt;: Integrate ViT for image feature extraction and GPT for text generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Define Loss Functions&lt;/strong&gt;: Use suitable loss functions for image and text components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training Loop&lt;/strong&gt;: Implement a training loop to update model parameters based on the image-text pairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;from transformers import Trainer, TrainingArguments

# Define training arguments
training_args = TrainingArguments(
    output_dir=&#39;./results&#39;,
    num_train_epochs=3,
    per_device_train_batch_size=4,
    logging_dir=&#39;./logs&#39;,
)

# Initialize Trainer
trainer = Trainer(
    model=image_model,  # This would be a combined model in practice
    args=training_args,
    train_dataset=train_dataset,  # Prepare your dataset
)

# Train the model
trainer.train()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-model-validation-and-evaluation&#34;&gt;4. Model Validation and Evaluation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective&lt;/strong&gt;: Assess the performance of the fine-tuned model to ensure it meets the desired criteria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Validation Set&lt;/strong&gt;: Use a separate dataset to validate the model’s performance during training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluation Metrics&lt;/strong&gt;: Measure performance using metrics such as accuracy, F1 score, or BLEU score (for text generation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;# Evaluate the model
eval_results = trainer.evaluate()
print(eval_results)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-export-and-deployment-to-hugging-face&#34;&gt;5. Export and Deployment to Hugging Face&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objective&lt;/strong&gt;: Make the fine-tuned model available for inference and integration through Hugging Face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Export the Model&lt;/strong&gt;: Save the fine-tuned model and tokenizer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upload to Hugging Face&lt;/strong&gt;: Use the &lt;code&gt;transformers&lt;/code&gt; library to push the model to the Hugging Face Hub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create an Inference Endpoint&lt;/strong&gt;: Deploy the model and set up an API endpoint for user interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;from transformers import pipeline

# Load model from Hugging Face Hub
nlp = pipeline(&amp;quot;text-generation&amp;quot;, model=&amp;quot;username/satgpt-model&amp;quot;)

# Use the model
result = nlp(&amp;quot;Describe the land cover of this GISTDA satellite image.&amp;quot;)
print(result)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;additional-concepts&#34;&gt;Additional Concepts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)&lt;/strong&gt;: Combines document retrieval with generative models to improve response accuracy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vision Transformers (ViT)&lt;/strong&gt;: Adapt transformers for image processing by treating images as sequences of patches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;formula-for-self-attention-in-rag&#34;&gt;Formula for Self-Attention in RAG&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In RAG, the attention mechanism can be described as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$[ \text{RAG}(Q, K, V, D) = \text{Attention}(Q, K, V) + \text{Retrieval}(D) ]$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $( D )$ represents retrieved documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;vision-transformer-vit&#34;&gt;Vision Transformer (ViT)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Vision Transformer treats images as sequences of patches and processes them with transformer architectures. The key operation in ViT involves:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$[ \text{Patch Embedding}(I) = \text{Linear}(I) + \text{Positional Encoding} ]$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $( I )$ is the image and the output is a sequence of patch embeddings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;full-flow-diagram&#34;&gt;Full Flow Diagram&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a conceptual flow of how data is processed through SatGPT, from input to output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Input&lt;/strong&gt;: Satellite Image + Textual Description&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image Processing&lt;/strong&gt;: ViT processes image into feature vectors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Text Generation&lt;/strong&gt;: GPT-2 generates textual descriptions from image features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Output&lt;/strong&gt;: Generated Text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;quick-thoughts-on-llms-before-we-wrap-up-this-blog&#34;&gt;Quick thoughts on LLMs before we wrap up this blog:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-introduction-to-large-language-models-llms-in-remote-sensing&#34;&gt;1. &lt;strong&gt;Introduction to Large Language Models (LLMs) in Remote Sensing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Large Language Models (LLMs) are advanced models designed to understand and generate human-like text. They can be adapted for analyzing satellite imagery by combining multimodal inputs, like images and textual descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equations&#34;&gt;Key Equations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underlying architecture for LLMs is based on the Transformer model, which is governed by:
$[
\mathbf{Z} = \text{softmax}\left(\frac{\mathbf{QK}^\top}{\sqrt{d_k}}\right)\mathbf{V}
]$
where $\mathbf{Q}, \mathbf{K}, \mathbf{V}$ are query, key, and value matrices respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-foundation-models-and-their-role-in-llms&#34;&gt;2. &lt;strong&gt;Foundation Models and Their Role in LLMs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foundation models are pre-trained on extensive datasets and serve as the base for fine-tuning on specific tasks, such as satellite image analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equations-1&#34;&gt;Key Equations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective during pre-training is to minimize:
$[
MLM = - \sum_{i=1}^{N} \log P(x_i | x_{-i}; \theta)
]$
where ${MLM}$ is the masked language modeling loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-training-vs-fine-tuning-vs-pre-trained-models-in-llms&#34;&gt;3. &lt;strong&gt;Training vs Fine-tuning vs Pre-trained Models in LLMs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pre-trained Models&lt;/strong&gt;: Trained on large-scale datasets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fine-tuning&lt;/strong&gt;: Adapting a pre-trained model to a specific task or dataset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training&lt;/strong&gt;: Training a model from scratch using a domain-specific dataset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equations-2&#34;&gt;Key Equations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cross-entropy loss function used during fine-tuning:
$[
\mathcal{L} = - \sum_{i=1}^{N} y_i \log(\hat{y}_i)
]$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-how-to-train-llms-on-satellite-images&#34;&gt;4. &lt;strong&gt;How to Train LLMs on Satellite Images&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Training LLMs on satellite images involves using multimodal inputs and embeddings to represent both images and textual descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- #### Key Equations
The multimodal training objective is:
$\[
\mathcal{L}_{\text{multimodal}} = \lambda \cdot \mathcal{L}_{\text{img}} + (1-\lambda) \cdot \mathcal{L}_{\text{text}}
\]$ --&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-retrieval-augmented-generation-rag-for-satellite-image-analysis&#34;&gt;5. &lt;strong&gt;Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) for Satellite Image Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAG combines document retrieval with generation capabilities to enhance satellite image analysis by incorporating additional contextual information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equations-3&#34;&gt;Key Equations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAG combines retrieval and generation via:
$[
P(x|c) = \sum_{i} P(x | c_i, q)P(c_i | q)
]$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-using-langchain-for-satellite-image-llm-applications&#34;&gt;6. &lt;strong&gt;Using LangChain for Satellite Image LLM Applications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LangChain facilitates chaining LLMs together for various tasks, such as preprocessing, analysis, and post-processing of satellite images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;example&#34;&gt;Example&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using LangChain to preprocess satellite metadata:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;from langchain import SimplePromptTemplate
template = SimplePromptTemplate(prompt=&amp;quot;Summarize satellite data: {data}&amp;quot;)
summary = template.run(data=satellite_metadata)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;7-sample-datasets-for-llm-fine-tuning-in-remote-sensing&#34;&gt;7. &lt;strong&gt;Sample Datasets for LLM Fine-Tuning in Remote Sensing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Datasets such as UC Merced Land Use, EuroSAT, and BigEarthNet are used for fine-tuning LLMs to handle specific satellite image tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;8-mathematical-foundations-of-attention-mechanisms-in-llms&#34;&gt;8. &lt;strong&gt;Mathematical Foundations of Attention Mechanisms in LLMs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attention mechanism in LLMs is crucial for focusing on specific parts of the input data, such as regions in a satellite image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equations-4&#34;&gt;Key Equations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-attention mechanism:
$[
\text{Attention}(Q, K, V) = \text{softmax}\left(\frac{QK^\top}{\sqrt{d_k}}\right)V
]$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;9-multimodal-llm-architectures-for-satellite-images&#34;&gt;9. &lt;strong&gt;Multimodal LLM Architectures for Satellite Images&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multimodal LLMs integrate both text and image data, allowing for comprehensive analysis of satellite imagery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equations-5&#34;&gt;Key Equations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For multimodal learning, image and text representations are combined:
$[
\mathbf{Z} = \text{Concat}(Z_{\text{img}}, Z_{\text{text}})
]$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;10-preprocessing-techniques-for-satellite-images-in-llms&#34;&gt;10. &lt;strong&gt;Preprocessing Techniques for Satellite Images in LLMs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preprocessing techniques like normalization and histogram equalization are essential for preparing satellite images for analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-formulas&#34;&gt;Key Formulas&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image normalization:
$[
X&amp;rsquo; = \frac{X - \mu}{\sigma}
]$
where $X$ is the pixel value, $\mu$ is the mean, and $\sigma$ is the standard deviation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;11-handling-illumination-and-atmospheric-effects-in-llms&#34;&gt;11. &lt;strong&gt;Handling Illumination and Atmospheric Effects in LLMs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illumination and atmospheric distortions can affect satellite images, and models must be trained to handle these variations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equations-6&#34;&gt;Key Equations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illumination adjustment formula:
$[
I&amp;rsquo; = \frac{I}{\cos(\theta) + \epsilon}
]$
where $\theta$ is the solar zenith angle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;12-self-supervised-learning-ssl-for-satellite-image-analysis&#34;&gt;12. &lt;strong&gt;Self-Supervised Learning (SSL) for Satellite Image Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SSL techniques allow models to learn from unlabelled satellite data by setting up proxy tasks such as predicting missing data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- 
#### Key Equations
Contrastive loss function in SSL:
$\[
\mathcal{L}_{\text{contrastive}} = - \log \frac{\exp(\mathbf{z}_i^\top \mathbf{z}_j / \tau)}{\sum_{k} \exp(\mathbf{z}_i^\top \mathbf{z}_k / \tau)}
\]$ --&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;13-open-source-tools-for-llms-in-satellite-image-analysis&#34;&gt;13. &lt;strong&gt;Open-Source Tools for LLMs in Satellite Image Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Useful tools include Hugging Face Transformers for fine-tuning, LangChain for chaining models, and FastAI for data augmentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;example-code&#34;&gt;Example Code&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Hugging Face Transformers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;from transformers import BertTokenizer, BertModel
tokenizer = BertTokenizer.from_pretrained(&amp;quot;bert-base-uncased&amp;quot;)
model = BertModel.from_pretrained(&amp;quot;bert-base-uncased&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;14-fine-tuning-llms-for-specific-satellite-image-tasks&#34;&gt;14. &lt;strong&gt;Fine-Tuning LLMs for Specific Satellite Image Tasks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fine-tuning involves adjusting a pre-trained model using satellite data to improve performance on specific tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-steps&#34;&gt;Key Steps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Load a pre-trained model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freeze initial layers and fine-tune top layers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Train with domain-specific data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;15-evaluation-metrics-for-llms-in-remote-sensing&#34;&gt;15. &lt;strong&gt;Evaluation Metrics for LLMs in Remote Sensing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evaluating the performance of Large Language Models (LLMs) in remote sensing involves several metrics, including precision, recall, F1 score, mean Average Precision (mAP), and BLEU score. These metrics help assess the quality of predictions and the relevance of generated content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-metrics&#34;&gt;Key Metrics&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Precision and Recall&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Precision&lt;/strong&gt; measures the proportion of true positive results among all positive results predicted by the model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recall&lt;/strong&gt; measures the proportion of true positive results among all actual positive results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equations-7&#34;&gt;Key Equations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Precision:
$[
\text{Precision} = \frac{TP}{TP + FP}
]$
Recall:
$[
\text{Recall} = \frac{TP}{TP + FN}
]$
where $TP$ is true positives, $FP$ is false positives, and $FN$ is false negatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F1 Score&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;F1 Score&lt;/strong&gt; is the harmonic mean of precision and recall, providing a single metric that balances both.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equation&#34;&gt;Key Equation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$[
\text{F1} = 2 \cdot \frac{\text{Precision} \cdot \text{Recall}}{\text{Precision} + \text{Recall}}
]$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mean Average Precision (mAP)&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mAP&lt;/strong&gt; evaluates the precision of object detection models, averaging the precision across different recall levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equation-1&#34;&gt;Key Equation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Average Precision (AP) for a single class:
$[
\text{AP} = \int_{0}^{1} \text{Precision}(r) , \text{Recall}(r)
]$
where $\text{Precision}(r)$ is the precision at recall level $r$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mAP is the mean of AP across all classes:
$[
\text{mAP} = \frac{1}{C} \sum_{i=1}^{C} \text{AP}_i
]$
where $C$ is the number of classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BLEU Score&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BLEU Score&lt;/strong&gt; evaluates the quality of generated text by comparing it to reference texts, commonly used for tasks like image captioning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equation-2&#34;&gt;Key Equation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BLEU score is calculated using n-gram precision:
$[
\text{BLEU} = \text{exp}\left(\sum_{n=1}^{N} w_n \cdot \log P_n\right)
]$
where $P_n$ is the precision of n-grams, and $w_n$ is the weight for n-grams of length $n$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;example-code-1&#34;&gt;Example Code&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;from sklearn.metrics import precision_score, recall_score, f1_score
from sklearn.metrics import average_precision_score, precision_recall_curve
from nltk.translate.bleu_score import sentence_bleu

# Example for precision, recall, F1 score
y_true = [0, 1, 1, 0, 1, 1, 0]
y_pred = [0, 1, 0, 0, 1, 1, 1]
precision = precision_score(y_true, y_pred)
recall = recall_score(y_true, y_pred)
f1 = f1_score(y_true, y_pred)

# Example for BLEU score
reference = [[&#39;GISTDA&#39;, &#39;is&#39;, &#39;the&#39;, &#39;premier&#39;, &#39;place&#39;, &#39;to&#39;, &#39;work&#39;, &#39;in&#39;, &#39;the&#39;, &#39;geo&#39;, &#39;sector&#39;, &#39;in&#39;, &#39;thailand&#39;]]
candidate = [&#39;GISTDA&#39;, &#39;is&#39;, &#39;the&#39;, &#39;best&#39;, &#39;workplace&#39;, &#39;in&#39;, &#39;geo&#39;, &#39;in&#39;, &#39;thailand&#39;]
bleu_score = sentence_bleu(reference, candidate)

print(f&amp;quot;Precision: {precision}&amp;quot;)
print(f&amp;quot;Recall: {recall}&amp;quot;)
print(f&amp;quot;F1 Score: {f1}&amp;quot;)
print(f&amp;quot;BLEU Score: {bleu_score}&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;16-transfer-learning-for-satellite-imagery&#34;&gt;16. &lt;strong&gt;Transfer Learning for Satellite Imagery&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transfer learning uses models pre-trained on general datasets and adapts them for satellite image tasks through domain-specific fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- 
#### Key Equations
The total loss in transfer learning:
$\[
\mathcal{L}_{\text{total}} = \mathcal{L}_{\text{general}}(\theta_g) + \lambda \mathcal{L}_{\text{task}}(\theta_t)
\]$
where $\lambda$ is a regularization factor. --&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;example-code-2&#34;&gt;Example Code&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using pre-trained ResNet for satellite image classification:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;from torchvision import models
resnet = models.resnet50(pretrained=True)

# Freeze general layers
for param in resnet.parameters():
    param.requires_grad = False

# Fine-tune top layers
resnet.fc = nn.Linear(in_features=2048, out_features=num_classes)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;17-explainability-in-llms-for-remote-sensing-xai&#34;&gt;17. &lt;strong&gt;Explainability in LLMs for Remote Sensing (XAI)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explainable AI (XAI) methods enhance the transparency of LLM predictions, allowing users to understand how models make decisions based on satellite imagery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-techniques&#34;&gt;Key Techniques&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attention Visualization&lt;/strong&gt;: Shows which parts of the input data are focused on by the model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grad-CAM&lt;/strong&gt;: Generates heatmaps highlighting important regions in the satellite images.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SHAP&lt;/strong&gt;: Explains individual predictions by computing feature contributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-equations-8&#34;&gt;Key Equations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grad-CAM heatmap formula:
$[
\text{Grad-CAM}(A^k) = \text{ReLU}\left( \sum_k \alpha_k A^k \right)
]$
where $\alpha_k$ is the gradient of the loss with respect to the feature map $A^k$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;example-code-3&#34;&gt;Example Code&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Grad-CAM for explainability:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;import torch
import cv2
import numpy as np

# Compute gradients
def grad_cam(model, img):
    gradients = torch.autograd.grad(outputs=model(img), inputs=model.layer4)
    weights = torch.mean(gradients[0], dim=[2, 3], keepdim=True)
    cam = torch.sum(weights * model.layer4(img), dim=1)
    return cam

# Apply Grad-CAM on an image
cam_output = grad_cam(resnet, satellite_image)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, large language models (LLMs) are making impressive strides in the realm of satellite data analysis, showcasing their potential across scene understanding, localization, counting, and change detection. These models are beginning to transform how we interpret complex satellite imagery, offering valuable insights for everything from environmental monitoring to urban development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these advancements, challenges remain. Current benchmarks reveal that while LLMs excel in tasks like generating descriptive captions and recognizing landmarks, they sometimes fall short in areas requiring detailed object counting and nuanced change detection. This highlights the need for more refined evaluation methods to fully capture and enhance LLM capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As both satellite technology and LLMs continue to evolve, the path forward promises exciting developments. By refining benchmarks and exploring new methodologies, we can unlock even greater potential in this technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed this deep dive into the intersection of LLMs and satellite data. If you found this blog insightful, please consider sharing it with others who might be interested. Stay tuned for more updates and innovations in this thrilling field!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;Citation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panboonyuen, Teerapong. (Sep 2024). &lt;em&gt;How to Fine-Tune and Deploy a Satellite-Specific LLM Model for Satellite Images&lt;/em&gt;. Blog post on Kao Panboonyuen. &lt;a href=&#34;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-09-09-how-to-fine-tune-and-deploy-a-satellite-specific-llm-model/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-09-09-how-to-fine-tune-and-deploy-a-satellite-specific-llm-model/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For a BibTeX citation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;@article{panboonyuen2024finetune,
  title   = &amp;quot;How to Fine-Tune and Deploy a Satellite-Specific LLM Model for Satellite Images&amp;quot;,
  author  = &amp;quot;Panboonyuen, Teerapong&amp;quot;,
  journal = &amp;quot;kaopanboonyuen.github.io/&amp;quot;,
  year    = &amp;quot;2024&amp;quot;,
  month   = &amp;quot;Sep&amp;quot;,
  url     = &amp;quot;https://kaopanboonyuen.github.io/blog/2024-09-09-how-to-fine-tune-and-deploy-a-satellite-specific-llm-model/&amp;quot;}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Did you find this page helpful? Consider sharing it 🙌
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vaswani, A., Shazeer, N., Parmar, N., Uszkoreit, J., Jones, L., Kaiser, Ł., Polosukhin, I. (NeurIPS 2017).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Attention Is All You Need.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)&lt;/em&gt;, 5998-6008. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3295222.3295349&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3295222.3295349&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brown, T., Mann, B., Ryder, N., Subbiah, M., Kaplan, J., Dhariwal, P., Shinn, E., Ramesh, A., Muthukrishnan, P., and others. (NeurIPS 2020).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Language Models are Few-Shot Learners.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)&lt;/em&gt;, 1877-1901. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3454337.3454731&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3454337.3454731&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Devlin, J., Chang, M. W., Lee, K., &amp;amp; Toutanova, K. (NAACL 2019).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;BERT: Pre-training of Deep Bidirectional Transformers for Language Understanding.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL)&lt;/em&gt;, 4171-4186. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3331189.3331190&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3331189.3331190&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dosovitskiy, A., Beyer, L., Kolesnikov, A., Weissenborn, D., Zhai, X., &amp;amp; others. (ICLR 2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;An Image is Worth 16x16 Words: Transformers for Image Recognition at Scale.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3453424.3453670&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3453424.3453670&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Radford, A., Wu, J., Child, R., Mehri, S., &amp;amp; others. (ICLR 2019).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Language Models are Unsupervised Multitask Learners.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3326452.3326458&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3326452.3326458&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clark, K., Luong, M. T., Le, Q. V., &amp;amp; Manning, C. D. (ACL 2019).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;ELECTRA: Pre-training Text Encoders as Discriminators Rather Than Generators.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)&lt;/em&gt;, 2251-2261. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3454375.3454420&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3454375.3454420&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zhang, Y., Zhao, Y., Saleh, M., &amp;amp; Liu, P. J. (ICLR 2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;PEGASUS: Pre-training with Extracted Gap-sentences for Abstractive Summarization.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3453104.3453140&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3453104.3453140&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kenton, J., &amp;amp; Toutanova, K. (NAACL 2019).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;BERT: Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL)&lt;/em&gt;, 4171-4186. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3331189.3331190&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3331189.3331190&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yang, Z., Yang, D., Dineen, C., &amp;amp; others. (ICLR 2020).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;XLNet: Generalized Autoregressive Pretraining for Language Understanding.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3456141.3456151&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3456141.3456151&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raffel, C., Shinn, E., S. J. McDonell, C. Lee, K., &amp;amp; others. (ICLR 2021).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Exploring the Limits of Transfer Learning with a Unified Text-to-Text Transformer.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.5555/3456181.3456210&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;doi:10.5555/3456181.3456210&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zhang, C., &amp;amp; Wang, S. (arXiv 2024).&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ldquo;Good at Captioning, Bad at Counting: Benchmarking GPT-4V on Earth Observation Data.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;arXiv preprint arXiv:2401.17600&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17600&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;arxiv.org/abs/2401.17600&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
